<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid>umich-bhl-86354</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Finding Aid for Dean C. Worcester Papers</titleproper><author>Finding aid prepared by: Bentley Historical Library staff</author></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Bentley Historical Library</publisher><p><date>1960?</date></p></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2022-10-07 12:17:31 -0400</date>.</creation><langusage>The finding aid is written in <language encodinganalog="language" langcode="eng">English.</language></langusage></profiledesc><revisiondesc><change><date>2015-07-28</date><item>Added written notes from paper finding aid.</item></change><change><date>2003-10-10</date><item>Converted to EAD2002 using Word macro and Xmetal</item></change><change><date>1999-06-09</date><item>Converted to EAD version 1.0 using WORD 6 macro and some hand tagging and converted to new container style.</item></change><change><date>1998-08</date><item>Original encoding from Word 6.0 file</item></change><change><date>2016-11-21</date><item>Updated Conditions Governing Use Note</item></change><change><date>2022-01-31</date><item>updated related materials note</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader><frontmatter><titlepage><publisher>Bentley Historical Library <lb/>University of Michigan</publisher><titleproper>Finding Aid for Dean C. Worcester Papers</titleproper><author>Finding aid prepared by: Bentley Historical Library staff</author></titlepage></frontmatter><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Bentley Historical Library</corpname>
      <extptr actuate="onload" href="bhladd" show="embed"/>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Dean C. Worcester papers</unittitle>
    <origination label="creator">
      <persname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86828116" source="lcnaf">Worcester, Dean C. (Dean Conant), 1866-1924</persname>
    </origination>
    <unitid type="call number">86354 Aa/2, Ac</unitid>
    <physdesc>
      <extent>4.4 linear feet</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <physdesc>
      <extent>1 oversize folder</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate normal="1887/1925" type="inclusive">1887-1925</unitdate>
    <langmaterial id="aspace_ad58ecc0efc5b4225eab51a6a2a9f9ec">The materials are in <language encodinganalog="041" langcode="eng">English.</language></langmaterial>
    <abstract id="aspace_59e3371f780865d6c54421258e0cc9b6">University of Michigan professor of zoology and museum curator, participated in or and led several research expeditions to the Philippines, member of the First and Second Philippine Commissions and involved in several Philippines business ventures; records includes notes, correspondence, publications and photographs relating to research expeditions, service on Philippines Commissions business activities, of special interest are notes of a trip taken to Mindoro and Palawan in July of 1910 and papers pertaining to the special Wood-Forbes Investigating Mission to the Philippines in 1921.</abstract>
  </did>
  <descgrp type="admin">
    <acqinfo><p>The collection was donated in 1957 by Alice Worcester Day (Mrs. Kenneth B. Day). Mrs. Day was Dean C. Worcester's daughter. Donor no. <num encodinganalog="541$e" type="donor">3253</num></p></acqinfo>
    <accessrestrict><p>The collection is open for research.</p></accessrestrict>
    <userestrict><p>Anne Day Harrell, daughter of Alice W. Day, has transferred any applicable copyright in her grandfather's papers to the Regents of the University of Michigan but the collection may contain third-party materials for which copyright was not transferred. Patrons are responsible for determining the appropriate use or reuse of materials.</p></userestrict>
    <prefercite><p>item, folder title, box no., Dean C. Worcester Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>
  </descgrp>
  <bioghist>  <chronlist>
    <head>Worcester Chronology</head>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1866</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Born, Thetford, Vermont</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1887-1888</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Visited the Philippines with Joseph Beal Steere expedition sponsored by the University of Michigan</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1889</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Graduated from the University of Michigan</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1890-1893</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Visited the Philippines as leader of the Menage expedition sponsored by the Minnesota Academy of Natural Science</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1893</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Appointed instructor at the University of Michigan</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1895</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Promoted to assistant professor of zoology and appointed curator of the University Museum, University of Michigan</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1898</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Published <title render="italic">The Philippine Islands and their People</title></event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1899</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Appointed to the First Philippine Commission, visited the Philippines with the commission, and supervised compilation of commission's final report</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1900</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Appointed to the Second Philippine Commission and returned to the Philippines</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1901</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Appointed Secretary of the Interior in the Philippine Commission's government of the Philippines</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1913</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Resigned position with the Philippine Commission and became vice-president of the Philippine-American Company</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1914</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Published <title render="italic">The Philippines Past and Present</title></event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1913-1924</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Worked at various business enterprises in the Philippines</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
    <chronitem>
      <date>1924</date>
      <eventgrp>
        <event>Died in Manila</event>
      </eventgrp>
    </chronitem>
  </chronlist>
<p>Dean Conant Worcester was born in Thetford, Vermont, the youngest son of an impoverished family of nine children. In 1884, his older brother and sister paid his expenses to the University of Michigan where he majored in zoology and came under the influence of Joseph B. Steere, chair of the Department of Zoology. In 1887, still an undergraduate, Worcester joined Steer's expedition to the Philippines, financing the costs by insuring his life and borrowing on the policy.</p><p> The Steere expedition was recognized as a scientific success. With academic credit for his participation in the expedition and a semester's work in zoology, Worcester obtained his A.B. degree in 1889. He and Frank Bourns, also of the Steere expedition, planned a longer sojourn in the Philippines and found financing through the University of Minnesota and a wealthy Minneapolis businessman Louis F. Menage. The Menage Expedition, 1890-1893, resulted in the collection of over three thousand specimens of birds, bats, butterflies, reptiles, mammals, corals, shells and in ethnological material. Upon his return, Worcester married Nanon Fay Leas and in the autumn of 1893 became an instructor in animal morphology at the University of Michigan. He began publishing monographs on Philippine birds, with Bourns and alone, and in 1895 he was promoted to assistant professor of zoology and appointed curator of the Zoological Museum.</p><p> In 1897 Worcester delivered his first general public lecture on the Philippines to the Unity Club of Ann Arbor and in that same year published his first general article on the Philippines, "Spanish Rule in the Philippines, co-authored with Bourns. With Dewey's victory over the Spanish in Manila Bay (May 1, 1898), Worcester began to think of the exciting prospect of the Philippines as an American colony. During a six week period, July 10 to September 1, 1898, Worcester wrote a very successful book <title render="italic">The Philippine Islands and Their People</title>, based on the letters he had written home during his scientific expeditions. A few months later, and as the McKinley government moved to extend American military control over the Philippine archipelago, a letter from his expedition colleague Frank Bourns warning of the danger of a Philippine insurgency led him to seek a meeting with President McKinley at which time he presented Bourns' views and augmented them with his own. McKinley asked Worcester to join a "civilian commission composed of men skilled in diplomacy and statesmanship" as requested by Admiral Dewey who was alarmed at the rejection by the newly declared Filipino government of the U.S. program of benevolent assimilation.</p><p> Through his participation in both the First and Second Philippine Commissions and in his position of Secretary of the Interior in the Commission government from 1901 to 1913, Worcester continued to have great influence on the formulation and implementation of American policy in the Philippines. His tenure on the First and Second Philippine Commissions would be the longest of all the commissioners. Worcester's rejection of independence for the Philippines, first voiced in an 1899 interview with Dr. Apacible, a Philippine insurgent with whom Worcester met in Hong Kong on his voyage to the Philippines, would never waver.</p><p> In 1913 Worcester resigned his position with the Philippine Commission to become vice-president of the Philippine-American Company. The following year he published <title render="italic">The Philippines Past and Present</title> and continued to direct various business enterprises until his death. Worcester's influence on American colonial policy and the various and controversial roles he played in the Philippines from his first visit in 1887 to his death in Manila in 1924: scientist, government official, propagandist and entrepreneur, earned him both accolades and deep resentment.</p></bioghist>
  <arrangement><p>The Worcester collection covers the period of 1900 to 1924 and has been arranged into six series: Correspondence; Papers; Articles, lectures, etc.; Newspaper clippings; Miscellaneous; and Photographs.</p></arrangement>
  <scopecontent><p>The Dean C. Worcester papers filed at the Bentley Historical Library consist of correspondence, subject files, newspaper clippings, publications, and photographs pertaining to his activities in the Philippine Islands. Of interest are notes of a trip taken to Mindoro and Palawan in July of 1910 and papers pertaining to the special Wood-Forbes Investigating Mission to the Philippines in 1921. The collection includes correspondence with William Howard Taft and Leonard Wood.</p></scopecontent>
  <controlaccess>
    <p>
      <extptr actuate="onload" href="accnote" show="embed"/>
    </p>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Mindoro (Philippines)</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Palawan (Philippines)</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.</geogname>
    <subject source="lcsh">Voyages and travels.</subject>
    <subject source="lcsh">Americans -- Philippines.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Anthropology.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Colonists.</subject>
    <subject source="lcsh">Filipinos.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Philippines -- History -- Insurrection, 1899-1901.</geogname>
    <subject source="lcsh">Soldiers -- United States.</subject>
    <subject source="lcsh">Spaniards -- Philippines.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Warships.</subject>
    <genreform source="gmgpc">Caricatures.</genreform>
    <genreform source="aat">Photographs.</genreform>
    <genreform source="aat">Scrapbooks.</genreform>
    <corpname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79021846" source="lcnaf">University of Michigan -- Faculty.</corpname>
    <persname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86828116" source="lcnaf">Worcester, Dean C. (Dean Conant), 1866-1924.</persname>
    <persname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n97046996" source="lcnaf">Denby, Edwin, 1870-1929.</persname>
    <persname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50001670" source="lcnaf">Dewey, George, 1837-1917.</persname>
    <persname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86828116" source="lcnaf">Worcester, Dean C. (Dean Conant), 1866-1924.</persname>
    <persname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79022244" role="ctb" source="lcnaf">Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.</persname>
    <persname role="ctb" source="lcnaf">Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.</persname>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc type="combined"><c01 id="aspace_682686c230d35f017886917d1cce446d" level="series"><did><unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>Correspondence dates from 1907 to 1922, unfortunately not the period of Worcester's early service in the Philippines. Although there is a letter from Secretary of War William Howard Taft in 1907 relating to the Philippine government and independence, the bulk of the correspondence pertains to Worcester lectures and to his book <title render="italic">The Philippines Past and Present</title>.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_adcfbb68f2da0f81a27bb750fb0e10d8" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1907/1911" type="inclusive">1907-1911</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_e2b3a4d19822d8070d225bd260dd87bc" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1912/1912" type="inclusive">1912</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_12ff4046266da129daa2f852a74c5d04" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1913-01/1913-06" type="inclusive">January-June 1913</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_aaf25336d22d1e03dcb6d308b93ac401" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1913-07/1913-12" type="inclusive">July-December 1913</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_8416d5026f9bc0e16454bc68c330ba55" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1914-01/1914-06" type="inclusive">January-June 1914</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_1f920bd3e3020c890f45a6492b352898" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1914-07/1914-12" type="inclusive">July-December 1914</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_f34cfa693ce412430fe9042ed97060c1" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1915/1915" type="inclusive">1915</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_d034ca487798f1d2c9c7e510ece5bacd" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning lectures</unittitle><physdesc><extent>3 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1913/1915" type="inclusive">1913-1915</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_c1a14a1779031ef0fa14649a085c2663" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning <title render="italic">The Philippines Past and Present</title></unittitle><physdesc><extent>4 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1913/1922" type="inclusive">1913-1922</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_ba0a629fd67616d64ebd1a6e0cc363e5" level="series"><did><unittitle>Papers</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>Papers is a small series of files on specific topics. The files date from1910 to 1922 and concern such topics as the Wood-Forbes mission of 1921-22, disciplinary cases of government officials in 1911-1912, and Worcester's resignation from the Philippine Commission in 1913.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_609f657b9a664a4b3571564b7983cfd6" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning a trip to Mindoro and Palawan</unittitle><unitdate normal="1910/1910" type="inclusive">1910</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_cbbe43a05c7a09f68c6678115813d125" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning disciplinary cases of government officials</unittitle><physdesc><extent>2 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1911/1912" type="inclusive">1911-1912</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_2c50794b180cb02109261c51f750e2a1" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning the production of a film on the Philippines</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1913" type="inclusive">1911-1913</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_1ff50ff84bbe2ab5a76c910a5212652f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Include data used in writing <title render="italic">The Philippines Past and Present</title></unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1913" type="inclusive">1911-1913</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_f7f9db7541a266bc8b73f94d9a0a89c8" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning attempts to transfer jurisdiction over the Philippine General Hospital to the University of the Philippines</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1912" type="inclusive">1912</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_54d25a7ed2de238752e7b239f13e10f3" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning Gen. Henry Bandholtz</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1912" type="inclusive">1912</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_14fb47014e1e06ecc716b3e31ce40fc9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Relating to Worcester's resignation from Philippine Commission</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1913" type="inclusive">1913</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_12c36e6cdb6c6ff0019b0a41afcddc75" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning speech by Winfred P. Denison</unittitle><physdesc><extent>3 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1914/1914" type="inclusive">1914</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_6f15e82b9b82b2145f38bccbf73d792e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning miscellaneous topics</unittitle><physdesc><extent>3 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1914/1925" type="inclusive">1914-1925</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_10cc208080b9219f245fe7a1f92e3968" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning Wood-Forbes mission to Philippines</unittitle><unitdate normal="1921/1922" type="inclusive">1921-1922</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_f6c11b9be07d9efe603ee9e2063fc08b" level="series"><did><unittitle>Articles, lectures, etc.</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>Articles, lectures, etc. is a series that covers the period of 1898 to 1915. The materials all relate to affairs of the Philippine Islands.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_93fd2de949c48b3bb5a5ad80ec2caad9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Articles and undated, concerning the Philippines</unittitle><physdesc><extent>5 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1898/1915" type="inclusive">1898-1915</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_7ea33e5988b80a8174e54efa82985aab" level="file"><did><unittitle>Lecture given at the Y.M.C.A.</unittitle><unitdate normal="1910/1910" type="inclusive">1910</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_12b7343bdec3d3450f51b78c3d69efc6" level="file"><did><unittitle>Lectures and speeches and undated, concerning the Philippines</unittitle><physdesc><extent>5 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1908/1913" type="inclusive">1908-1913</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ac2e3242e40a04b3cbb2777f24485afd" level="file"><did><unittitle>Newspaper interviews</unittitle><unitdate normal="1899/1915" type="inclusive">1899-1915</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_1fbb4e0f6fdd60768e71c583fec03f01" level="file"><did><unittitle>Note cards</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_c5ebc869a9cf6e72ea7444c05cf3e67c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Report</unittitle><unitdate normal="1910/1910" type="inclusive">1910</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(extracts)</p></odd></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_8a00e18f8c47a5410bb5a3cf03c4a59b" level="series"><did><unittitle>Newspaper clippings</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>The Newspaper clippings cover the years 1898 to 1915 with some gaps. The clippings are from both English and Spanish language newspapers and document Worcester's activities, speeches he gave, and reviews and assessments of his published studies of the Philippine Islands.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_93c4a4ec04494cbd371e16c501ac4655" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning <title render="italic">The Philippine Islands and their People</title></unittitle><unitdate normal="1898/1898" type="inclusive">1898</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_7344c913b108a4e6ce99177d2fe5d653" level="file"><did><unittitle>Accounts of speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1899/1899" type="inclusive">1899</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_0031bd149faf31bba5fcd22962c1618f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning Worcester's activities in the Philippines</unittitle><physdesc><extent>3 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1913/1913" type="inclusive">1913</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_414ee53ffc98112d7c0d46d5fd8537ce" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning lectures</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1914" type="inclusive">1913-1914</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_710110a374b18cc58e05644fd71626e5" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning lectures</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1914" type="inclusive">1914</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_e25c07a16338d90edfd115f96a11502b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Concerning <title render="italic">The Philippines Past and Present</title></unittitle><physdesc><extent>3 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1914/1914" type="inclusive">1914</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_db57bf23ec651bc22ada7accc26cb399" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle><physdesc><extent>10 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1899/1915" type="inclusive">1899-1915</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_13d30e2f51e857bc3223bd134e7b0e0f" level="series"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>Miscellaneous contains issues of the Annual Report of the Secretary of the Interior to the Philippine Commission, reprints of Worcester's articles on the Philippines, and collected articles and published materials.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_befeb516568aa0b10f223ff79340ab23" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellanea</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_116373424a8062064b3bbfb311feb429" level="file"><did><unittitle>Plans for Worcester's Manila house</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1915" type="inclusive">1915</unitdate><container label="Oversize Folder" type="folder">Ac</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_db951d39f516307d59462d1dcbf04c18" level="file"><did><unittitle><title render="italic">Annual Report of the Secretary of the Interior to the Philippine Commission</title></unittitle><unitdate normal="1908/1908" type="inclusive">1908</unitdate><unitdate normal="1910/1913" type="inclusive">1910-1913</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_368d0891857a508c236784d5a15fc39f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous printed material, including reprints of articles</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_dfa0e10651d722395932f1f1623ff105" level="series"><did><unittitle><genreform normal="Photographs">Photographs</genreform></unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>The Photographs series represent an accumulation of images documenting Philippine life and culture. Many of these photographs were used in Worcester's book <title render="italic">The Philippines, Past and Present</title>.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_2c35d4d130f6e9fb21f05f93de0ada98" level="file"><did><unittitle>Philippines</unittitle><unitdate normal="1887/1893" type="inclusive">1887-1893</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><c03 id="aspace_9f9507b5467c9ece3aa376cc9d6742df" level="file"><did><unittitle>Agriculture</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_6ab9fa30ca218e925f320c03ffdc0bfd" level="file"><did><unittitle>Artifacts</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_b9ecc2040b20e50205e6226769e79676" level="file"><did><unittitle>Botany</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_59a46ef94f8b983c8e8c64e3a2d15dcd" level="file"><did><unittitle>Geography</unittitle></did><c04 id="aspace_0056fb397d2405290836bb6ffc44b48a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Guimaras</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_47c42e6680172a8b93df4cbc119da7df" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jolo</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_d385af3b15aa9338e1f5415c27f23b0a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Manila</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_5a89e890d976346ea6e83c76716772a2" level="file"><did><unittitle>Mindoro</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_5879fbf203324e7f904c0076d4fc9ef7" level="file"><did><unittitle>Negros</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_554e8b923bf7e065abc58d06c04a0184" level="file"><did><unittitle>Siquijor</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_35c62aa3942b79c0811c3712efe12f55" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04></c03><c03 id="aspace_ddc5ab7033ee50af8dc2b1840580fcfc" level="file"><did><unittitle>Industries</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_bdfa6351cc448ea173e1a96bb8f67dd3" level="file"><did><unittitle>Native groups</unittitle></did><c04 id="aspace_22ae794d2a800764d5cb70ae01f863b2" level="file"><did><unittitle>Mangyans of Mount Halcon, Mindoro</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_6ec05b7a68f8f9b5198d66f837a84296" level="file"><did><unittitle>Mangyans, Miscellaneous</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_a381b8ffb2c8d420b146a38da87da439" level="file"><did><unittitle>Moros of Jolo</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_3d59e2a99feddfe1f007c39e737b6684" level="file"><did><unittitle>Spaniards and mestizos</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_6cfa4e42517f559c4d9a0cabc7d90ffb" level="file"><did><unittitle>Tagalogs of Mindoro</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_374d774255e6e40af11f4badd67c4332" level="file"><did><unittitle>Tagbanuas of Palawan</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_57fc29ac99e7ed78198774c456530c61" level="file"><did><unittitle>Visayans of Negros</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04></c03><c03 id="aspace_14a063fa5d2924e78667180fd493d44f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Zoology</unittitle></did><c04 id="aspace_7808428981ac8d1f9da27b545e4cecbb" level="file"><did><unittitle>Mammals</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_4b80975fe78359001226978b9ebb81e0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04></c03><c03 id="aspace_517522504d7ea86317d0cb6bbab3b50f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Unidentified people</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_7552e26a9f53c30da9b19368edf8146f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Unidentified places</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_5d7cf04495db7508823f86bf83fcf25c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_aacb6c17680cb4711588ddf84a725ac5" level="file"><did><unittitle>Duplicates</unittitle><physdesc><extent>2 folders</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_5179f3c7651d97a7946836a10b8d050e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Philippines</unittitle><unitdate normal="1899/1913" type="inclusive">1899-1913</unitdate></did><c03 id="aspace_3c3b6f99bfce9b321c12829618d200af" level="file"><did><unittitle>Current history</unittitle></did><c04 id="aspace_28c9e78753e89a44401eb831904d6de2" level="file"><did><unittitle>Insurrection</unittitle></did><c05 id="aspace_ebad34b2a8db23665c9ac67c8d174a63" level="file"><did><unittitle>Caloocan</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05><c05 id="aspace_83b309d4faf80f7c1403b4af91e7c14a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Fort San Antonio Abad</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05><c05 id="aspace_2813a418e5d244db9ee1913ececd4fe5" level="file"><did><unittitle>Imus</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05><c05 id="aspace_f5d8b1ae83c36ef2661c445508cc11ee" level="file"><did><unittitle>Malabon</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05><c05 id="aspace_69ccd5198076fb7034dfc977033b7d1e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Parañaque</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05><c05 id="aspace_c5a107acfe30e3dafa692d10f159f4de" level="file"><did><unittitle>Pasig</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05><c05 id="aspace_b5a8d8153adb4e8958db9b4778186f7f" level="file"><did><unittitle>San Pedro Macate</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05><c05 id="aspace_82c7b320a5085c06baa77942a107b5dd" level="file"><did><unittitle>Zapote River</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05><c05 id="aspace_0f3c5723a229075864f44316fd04208b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05></c04><c04 id="aspace_5cf02898f4b317cf746083b7a528c77b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Manila scenes</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_1c686120f6770b6b17e7c0984c22d5f9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous persons</unittitle></did><c05 id="aspace_9f310f561f54c870c57e4fb34e9335a3" level="file"><did><unittitle>Americans</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05><c05 id="aspace_23c4f059fa6a882cc4b59db1fed655dc" level="file"><did><unittitle>Filipinos, Spaniards, etc.</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c05></c04><c04 id="aspace_54369c3e07de40736a166d73347f0a8b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Philippine Commission</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_ae65e78e7158c5982fc3aef0b5fd827a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Spanish fleet wreckage</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_3ef2bd06f748080757fa26ab84f0f478" level="file"><did><unittitle>United States fleet</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04></c03><c03 id="aspace_974b4570d1e4b4b36471d3ecdb3de181" level="file"><did><unittitle>Flagellants at Balintawak</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_746c0adc8eaf1786f2eda752f49aa30a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Industries</unittitle></did><c04 id="aspace_dd8c9c4227d272d00f9ec783f3307222" level="file"><did><unittitle>Fishing</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_38f420aeb75cedf8cf7e82598afd30c6" level="file"><did><unittitle>Transportation</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_174ca0cc0ff81035352c486975728ae0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c04></c03><c03 id="aspace_16c2879153263155ced0adbb8be7c0f0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Zoology</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_56884903752560f56703ff9037151495" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_2715bb95424c50d0aefbd7951515f4a9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Album, unidentified</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_07a7c9cea0f4f46bb51e2e9774f69249" level="file"><did><unittitle>Canada</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_48d4e73c6e513b87e5732689ce1eaf43" level="file"><did><unittitle>Europe</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_7cbacac924ef339eec8a9a2a7bffe3ae" level="file"><did><unittitle>Hong Kong</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_f52f8fdd749feb6764bb90381b82c76d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Japan</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_acb78f713eb6dee98e86cb9693f83448" level="file"><did><unittitle>List of negatives taken in 1899, 1900 by Dean C. Worcester and P.L. Sherman</unittitle><unitdate normal="1899/1900" type="inclusive">1899-1900</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_81d399d63ae52770964eb69defbb55ad" level="file"><did><unittitle>Illustration captions from <title render="italic">Native Life in the Philippines</title></unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_99e976060d13a6439593aa74f848cb0b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Illustrations (with captions)</unittitle></did><c03 id="aspace_e406a214df5ca2fbc8f0429105da62fe" level="file"><did><unittitle>From <title render="italic">The Philippine Islands and their People</title> (1898)</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_f8d7a3ede78092bc2337dd1f55bd3a97" level="file"><did><unittitle>From <title render="italic">The Philippines Past and Present</title> (1914)</unittitle><physdesc><extent>2 folders</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_ea5617df96ceebf8773608839e8953cc" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous (unidentified)</unittitle></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_f17095a2ac9ccf7af41aff9cfcd5e281" level="file"><did><unittitle>Portraits</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did></c02></c01></dsc>
  <descgrp type="add">
    <relatedmaterial>
      <head>Related Collections in other repositories</head>
<p>Dean C. Worcester papers and photographs are located in a number of other repositories. From information gathered by the Michigan Historical Collections and by the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology, the following have been identified:</p><p> Rare Books and Special Collections, University of Michigan Libraries: 1700 items, including 24 volumes of correspondence and reports and 21 volumes of clippings. This collection is described in <title render="italic">Balita mula Maynila</title>, by Thomas E. Powers.</p><p> Thetford Historical Society, Thetford, Vermont: 10 linear feet.</p><p> Museum of Anthropology, University of Michigan: 4,775 negatives.</p><p> Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, Illinois: Between 5,000 and 10,000 negatives. These Worcester holdings are combined with several other collections of Philippine photographs.</p><p> Original prints of Worcester negatives are found in all the above collections, as well as in the Anthropological Archives of the U.S. National Museum, American Museum of Natural History, Peabody Museum of Harvard University, and Rautenstrauch-Joest Museum in Cologne, Germany.</p>    </relatedmaterial>
  </descgrp>
</archdesc>
</ead>
