<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid>umich-bhl-2019013</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Finding aid for the Harold Dunbar Corbusier papers, 1883-1979</titleproper><author>Finding aid created by Nichole Manlove, July 2019.</author></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Bentley Historical Library</publisher></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2022-10-07 12:28:25 -0400</date>.</creation><langusage>The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage><descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules></profiledesc><revisiondesc><change><date>2019-08-12</date><item>Original encoding</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader><frontmatter><titlepage><publisher>Bentley Historical Library <lb/>University of Michigan</publisher><titleproper>Finding aid for the Harold Dunbar Corbusier papers, 1883-1979</titleproper><author>Finding aid created by Nichole Manlove, July 2019.</author></titlepage></frontmatter><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Bentley Historical Library</corpname>
      <extptr actuate="onload" href="bhladd" show="embed"/>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Harold Dunbar Corbusier papers</unittitle>
    <origination label="creator">
      <persname authfilenumber="https://lccn.loc.gov/n95092832" source="naf">Corbusier, Harold Dunbar, 1873-1950.</persname>
    </origination>
    <unitid type="call number">2019013 Aa 2 UAl</unitid>
    <physdesc>
      <extent>2. 4 linear feet (in 3 boxes)</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <physdesc>
      <extent>1 oversize folder</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1883/1979" type="inclusive">1883-1979 (scattered dates)</unitdate>
    <unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1902" type="bulk">1900-1902</unitdate>
    <abstract id="aspace_e223196148ddf731e20480433160dae3">An orthopedic surgeon in the United States Army, author, inventor, and University of Michigan alumnus (B.S. and M.D. 1899).  Corbusier served in the China Relief Expedition, the Philippines Campaign, the Mexican Border War, and World War I. 

The collection contains biographical information, correspondence, writings by Corbusier, collected articles and clippings, photographs and glass plate lantern slides, loose scrapbook materials, and a photo album. Materials document Corbusier's experiences during the China Relief Expedition, the Mexican Border War, the Philippines Campaign, and World War I.  The collection also contains a small amount of materials focusing on his time as a student at the University of Michigan, as well as to his medical and military careers.</abstract>
    <langmaterial id="aspace_12874c1bee0814346fb6d228e43e38eb">The material is in <language encodinganalog="041" langcode="eng">English</language>. Some program invitations are in <language encodinganalog="041" langcode="eng">French</language>, and <language encodinganalog="041" langcode="eng">Spanish</language>.</langmaterial>
  </did>
  <descgrp type="admin">
    <accessrestrict><p>This collection is open without restriction.</p></accessrestrict>
    <acqinfo><p>Donated by Thomas S. Knox (donor no. <num type="donor">11890</num>) in June 2018.</p></acqinfo>
    <accruals><p>No further additions to the records are expected.</p></accruals>
    <userestrict><p>Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan but the collection may contain third-party materials for which copyright is not held.  Patrons are responsible for determining the appropriate use or reuse of materials.</p></userestrict>
    <prefercite><p>[item], folder, box, Harold Dunbar Corbusier papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.</p></prefercite>
  </descgrp>
  <arrangement><p>The collection is arranged into 3 series: 1. Biographical, 1883-1950. 2. Correspondence, 1900-1979. 3. Visual Materials, 1898-1948.</p></arrangement>
  <bioghist><p><emph render="bold">Early Life and Education</emph></p><p>Harold Dunbar Corbusier (1873-1950) was born in Yavapai County, Arizona Territory to Colonel William H. and Fannie Dunbar Corbusier.  As a military family, the Corbusiers travelled between U.S. Army bases in Arizona, the Carolinas, Tennessee, Kansas, and the Midwest, including Fort Mackinac and Fort Wayne in Michigan (1882-1892). In 1893, Harold Corbusier entered the University of Michigan where he joined the Delta Upsilon Fraternity. He received both his Bachelor of Science and Medical degrees in 1899.</p><p>
<emph render="bold">Military Career</emph></p><p>After completing his education at the University of Michigan, Corbusier joined the Medical Department of the United States Army Reserve where he served in numerous military campaigns from 1900 to the end of World War I. From 1900 to 1905, Corbusier served as Acting Assistant Surgeon and in this capacity participated in the China Relief Expedition from 1900 to 1901 and in the Philippine Campaign from 1901 to 1902. Corbusier left active service in 1905, settling in Plainfield, NJ to raise a family with his wife Louise S. Corbusier, a Michigan native (1875-1964). The couple was married in 1930 and had two children, Frances (O'Brien) Corbusier and Nancy (Knox) Corbusier, born in 1913.   </p><p>
In 1909, Corbusier began his service with the National Guard of New Jersey.  In 1911, he joined the Organized Reserves (Army). In 1916, Corbusier began his service with the New Jersey Guard on the Mexican Border. Here he organized and commanded the Guard's first medical units, also known as the "Sanitary Train."  From 1917 to 1919, Corbusier served as a major in the United States Army Medical Corps.    </p><p>Corbusier was placed in a number of leadership positions during and immediately after World War I, specifically between 1916 and 1919.  He organized the Division of Orthopedic Surgery with the Surgeon General's Office (S.G.O.) subsequently serving as the Chief of Orthopedic Surgery.  He also organized the first Reconstruction Company in the U.S. for soldiers with physical challenges.  This system was later adopted by the War Department for Development Battalions.  Corbusier served as Chief of the Orthopedic Service and instructor at the Medical Officers' Training Camp in Fort Oglethorpe, GA and as Chief of the Orthopedic Section and training officer at Camp Meade, MD. Corbusier also served as the First Assistant to the Chief of the Orthopedic Service, and as Chief of the Reconstruction Section of General Hospital #3 in Colonia, NJ.  </p><p>
In 1920, Corbusier was promoted to Lieutenant Colonel of the Medical Section Officer's Reserve Corps. During this period, Corbusier was also appointed as U.S. Delegate to the International Congress of Arthritis. In 1922, he was appointed Chief Surgeon for the 12th Army Corps Reserve and circa 1931, he was promoted to Colonel in the Medical Corps (U.S. Army).  Between 1933 and 1948, Corbusier was also appointed as a U.S. Delegate to several International Congresses and travelled to Madrid, Brussels, Bucharest, Lima, and Havana. </p><p><emph render="bold">Medical Career</emph></p><p>After leaving active military service in 1905 and moving to Plainfield, NJ, Corbusier opened a private orthopedic clinic in 1908.  In 1911, he joined the hospital staff at Muhlenberg hospital in Plainfield where he organized the Department of Orthopedic Surgery and Physical Therapy. In 1913, he was appointed Junior Attending Surgeon in the Department of Surgery. That same year he was also appointed Clinical Assistant in the Department of Orthopedic Surgery at the New York Post-Graduate Medical School and Hospital. In 1916, Corbusier was appointed instructor in the Orthopedic Surgery Department. In 1923, Corbusier was named Muhlenberg hospital's Senior Attending Surgeon in Orthopedics. In 1936, he was appointed as Muhlenberg's Resident Consulting Surgeon. In 1945, he served as a consultant to the hospital's Physiotherapy Department.  </p><p>
<emph render="bold">Inventions</emph></p><p>Corbusier used his talents and knowledge of orthopedic medicine to pioneer the U.S. Army's system of reconstruction and devised a system of "Recruit Rehabilitation and Training in Development Battalions." The latter being a manpower salvage method adopted by the U.S. Army for all large military camps.  He also used his talents to design a special Army shoe known as the "Doughboy," that was worn by soldiers during WWI to counteract "Foot Weakness." He also designed the guidon, the first distinguishing flag used by the U.S. Army's Medical Department. </p><p> 
<emph render="bold">Civilian Life and Activities</emph> </p><p>Corbusier's civilian life was heavily intermingled with his military life. He served as an orthopedic and physio-therapeutic consultant to the Bureau of Public Health Service and as a consultant in Orthopedic Surgery and Physiotherapy to the Rehabilitation Commission of the American Legion in New Jersey, New York, and Connecticut.  He also lent his consultation services to the U.S. Senate Committee for the investigation of the Veteran's Bureau.  </p><p>Corbusier served as the President of the Association of Military Surgeons, President of the Academy of Physical Medicine of the United States, Vice-Chair of the Veterans of Foreign Wars National Rehabilitation Committee, Vice President of the American College of Physiotherapy, and Board member of the National Society for Crippled Children and Adults.  He lent his services to the American Red Cross, the Association of the Medical Reserve Corps, the College of International Surgeons, numerous Military Orders, and the University of Michigan Alumni Club. Corbusier also served as an honorary member of the Mexican Association of Military Surgeons and the Russian Veterans' Association. </p><p>Harold Dunbar Corbusier passed away on August 31, 1950, leaving behind a long and distinguished career as a retired Colonel, military surgeon, and civic leader. Louise S. Corbusier died on September 3, 1964.</p></bioghist>
  <scopecontent><p>The papers of Harold Dunbar Corbusier include a range of materials focusing on his medical and military career with the United States Army Medical Corps and the Medical Department of the U.S. Army Reserves between 1900 and ca. 1945. </p><p>The Biographical series included his biography, a diary reflecting on his childhood experiences at Fort Mackinac in Michigan, a typed manuscript highlighting his experiences during the Boxer Rebellion in China. Also included here are his professional publications and collected articles, event programs and invitations.</p><p>The Correspondence series primarily includes letters to his then fiancé Louise Shepard, as well as letters from military and governmental departments, hospitals, and other military and medical associations. 
images 
The Visual Materials series includes glass plate slides and a photo album with images of Chinese landmarks and troops from the eight nations fighting against the Boxers. Also included are photographs mostly focusing on the China and Philippines campaigns, and loose scrapbook materials (mostly clippings) focusing on China and Asia in general.  </p></scopecontent>
  <controlaccess>
    <p>
      <extptr actuate="onload" href="accnote" show="embed"/>
    </p>
    <geogname source="lcsh">China -- History -- Boxer Rebellion, 1899-1901.</geogname>
    <geogname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85024006" source="lcsh">China -- Description and travel.</geogname>
    <subject source="local">China Relief Expedition -- (1900-1901)</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Mexico -- History -- Revolution, 1910-1920.</geogname>
    <subject source="lctgm">Military life.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Military officers.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Philippines -- History -- Philippine American War, 1899-1902.</geogname>
    <occupation source="lcsh">Physicians.</occupation>
    <subject source="lcsh">World War I, 1914-1918.</subject>
    <genreform source="gmgpc">Diaries.</genreform>
    <genreform source="aat">Lantern slides.</genreform>
    <genreform source="gmgpc">Negatives.</genreform>
    <genreform source="aat">Photo albums.</genreform>
    <genreform source="lcsh">Photographs.</genreform>
    <genreform source="gmgpc">Scrapbooks.</genreform>
    <persname authfilenumber="https://lccn.loc.gov/n95092832" source="naf">Corbusier, Harold Dunbar, 1873-1950.</persname>
    <corpname rules="dacs">United States. Army. Medical Reserve Corps.</corpname>
    <corpname source="local">United States. War Department.</corpname>
    <corpname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79021846" source="lcnaf">University of Michigan -- Students.</corpname>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc type="combined"><c01 id="aspace_343805605928bb1a63934d87120efe7b" level="series"><did><unittitle>Biographical</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1883/1950" type="inclusive">1883-1950 (scattered dates)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>The Biographical series includes a typed biography, a diary reflecting on Corbusier's childhood experiences at Fort Mackinac, MI, a typed manuscript highlighting his experiences during the Boxer Rebellion, articles about Corbusier's medical, military, and civilian life, and his writings on the subject of orthopedics in military service published in <title render="italic">The Soldier's Foot</title> and <title render="italic">The Conservation of Man Power for War</title>.  </p><p>Also, collected materials from Corbusier's time at the University of Michigan (including a set of his handwritten class notes from Medical School, 1896-1897), special and general military orders, certificates pertaining to his medical, military, and civilian life endeavors, programs and invitations to international congresses and meetings. Collected materials also include a leather swatch from a "doughboy" boot. </p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_520c8e35b17550a795c95d98fe7021f4" level="file"><did><unittitle>Articles about Corbusier</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1917/1946" type="inclusive">1917-1946 (scattered dates)</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_5a1d0b4ddb9ed45fd8ec9e428be91d9c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Articles re: Military Campaigns</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1918" type="inclusive">Circa 1900-1918 (with gaps)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><scopecontent><p>Newspaper clippings about Corbusier, and the Boxer Rebellion in China.</p></scopecontent></c02><c02 id="aspace_1199c6c41d6b824bc56cd54698d7f50e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Biography</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_d058edc8ed2ebb3bb6740132fdc17081" level="file"><did><unittitle>Certificates, identification cards</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1950" type="inclusive">1900-1950 (scattered dates)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></did><c03 id="aspace_8774b2d33d33752c0d5a08f2bf9e0f43" level="file"><did><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1949" type="inclusive">1900-1949 (with gaps)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_b87267f9ea7ea52fb1ea561fb7fa1860" level="file"><did><physdesc><extent>1 oversize folder</extent></physdesc><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1910/1950" type="inclusive">1933-1950 (with gaps)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Oversize Folder" type="folder">1</container></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_2fcc7996bfe66ed3c05f2fa91be8cc3f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Collected Materials</unittitle><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><c03 id="aspace_785a74f76473a50c20f72d95a162f741" level="file"><did><unittitle>University of Michigan</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">1896-1949 (with gaps)</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Includes photographs)</p></odd></c03><c03 id="aspace_1cef5f3935c29e268a725c2a4884da16" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1936" type="inclusive">1900-1936 (scattered dates)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1936/1936" type="inclusive">1936</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Includes photographs)</p></odd></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_f1f7674987e51beb6db9b49e316dea3d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Diary</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1883/1892" type="inclusive">1883-1892</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_64d6c89f178e8f4784af991e2ed0ee6f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Military Orders</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1898/1941" type="inclusive">1898-1941 (scattered dates)</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_46911cc950725591760d634e88a707e5" level="file"><did><unittitle>Works authored by Corbusier</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1905/1943" type="inclusive">1905-1943 (scattered dates)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_a3799de644c42cb687058ba7eeb442b7" level="series"><did><unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1979" type="inclusive">1900-1979 (scattered dates)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>Of particular note in the Correspondence series are photocopies of over 61 handwritten letters to Corbusier's then fiancé Louise S. Shepard dating between 1900 and 1905.  These letters, which highlight Corbusier's military experiences, were written primarily during his time in China and in the Philippines.  </p><p>The series includes letters addressed to Corbusier from the military, from several medical associations, other governmental departments, and hospitals. In particular, materials include letters from the War Department regarding Corbusier's appointments and reappointments and letters from the Treasury Department's Bureau of Health Service regarding his appointment as an orthopedic and physio-therapeutic consultant. Also found here is correspondence from the Association of Military Surgeons of the United States regarding Corbusier's appointments as delegate to several international meetings on leprosy, pharmaceuticals, military medicine, and physiotherapy.  </p><p>The series also includes letters regarding Corbusier's nomination to Plainfield, NJ Board of Health, his appointment as Junior Attending Surgeon with the Muhlenberg Hospital, and his appointments with the New York Post-Graduate Medical School and Hospital.  Other items to note include membership letters to numerous organizations including the College of International Surgeons, and the Veterans of Foreign Wars National Rehabilitation Committee. </p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_33939e5cb59aa2059f0169902a84995f" level="file"><did><unittitle>To Corbusier</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1913/1950" type="inclusive">1913-1950 (scattered dates)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_0b74128f7635ebc4498be85f8adf4ff3" level="file"><did><unittitle>To Louise Shepard</unittitle><physdesc><extent>3 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1905" type="inclusive">1900-1905 (with gaps)</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_4c510715ba94d92f84c0f803608ffd1d" level="file"><did><unittitle>To Louise Shepard (transcribed letters)</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1902/1903" type="inclusive">1902-1903</unitdate><unitdate normal="1979/1979" type="inclusive">1979</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><scopecontent><p>Transcribed versions of letters written by Corbusier to his then fiance Louise Shepard between 1900 and 1903.  Also includes correspondence from 1979 between Nancy Knox (daughter) and the American Heritage Publishing Co.  The latter are in regard to a proposed article about the United States involvement with the Boxer Uprising in China.</p></scopecontent></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_5404a2a1f8f696990cf87de35dc022d5" level="series"><did><unittitle>Visual Materials</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1898/1948" type="inclusive">1898-1948 (scattered dates)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>The Visual Materials series includes labeled glass plate slides pertaining to the Boxer Rebellion as well as numerous photographs of the military campaigns in China and Mexico, and military training camps.  The series includes a photo album depicting locations in China, proofs and negatives with images relating to the China and Philippine campaigns, and loose scrapbook materials (mostly newspaper clippings) pertaining to China and Asia in general. The series also includes a number of photographs documenting Corbusier's civilian life.</p><p>In addition, a cloth map of North Eastern China (1900) and several cyanotype images of Queen Victoria's international funeral procession. </p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_64051377defe034797ce507773fe3d78" level="file"><did><unittitle>Glass Plate Slides</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></did><c03 id="aspace_0f262368f5f2777b86efe217c55a1214" level="file"><did><unittitle>HDC China Slides</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><scopecontent><p>Contains slides 1-111.</p></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_f970a863106b4520a4e3e82e6b2c61a7" level="file"><did><unittitle>China Slides Box I</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><scopecontent><p>Contains slides 113 - 161.  Missing slide 112.</p></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_f75d2e4b7e5bc260ff7e5742587a09aa" level="file"><did><unittitle>China Slides Box II</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><scopecontent><p>Contains slides 162 - 184.  Includes an unnumbered slide titled "Pekin Indians."</p></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_9bbf55a2ddaef04878df2c51ab4f98e6" level="file"><did><unittitle>Inventory list</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><scopecontent><p>Inventory list of slides as well as two cards (programs) regarding his presentation of the slides to the Historical Society of Plainfield and North Plainfield (New Jersey).</p></scopecontent></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_476b5dbc7b8fe2cff6945d78da380fc7" level="file"><did><unittitle>Map of North Eastern China</unittitle><unitdate normal="1900/1900" type="inclusive">1900</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Cloth map)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_63836517545421aca73a7bfd80ef4c2f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Photographs</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1936" type="inclusive">1900-1936 (scattered dates)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></did><c03 id="aspace_243c87a88e361f6d78988b498c91e6a0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Military Campaigns - China and Mexico</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1916" type="inclusive">1900-1916 (scattered dates)</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><scopecontent><p>Includes stereoscopic slides of Chinese Boxer soldiers, Chinese casualties, the Peiho River, guns from the H.M.S. "Terrible," and American and Japanese soldiers.</p></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_4e09bdb4580058b04229c3e75c573717" level="file"><did><unittitle>Photo album of China</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1900/1901" type="inclusive">1900-1901</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_89c2f2a8e07a5203c85e9458360f2d63" level="file"><did><unittitle>Proofs and Negatives re: China and the Philippines</unittitle><unitdate normal="1900/1900" type="inclusive">1900</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_b0c472a3029c6c681ee2fc09480255d4" level="file"><did><unittitle>Training Camps</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1915/1921" type="inclusive">1915, 1921</unitdate></did><c04 id="aspace_6df27439a52a08c2346617f6813102ea" level="file"><did><unittitle>Tobyhanna, PA</unittitle><unitdate normal="1921/1921" type="inclusive">1921</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c04><c04 id="aspace_6fc955241fcca3f67fb77d052c9a6f38" level="file"><did><unittitle>Tobyhanna, PA and Fort Oglethorpe, GA</unittitle><physdesc><extent>1 oversize folder</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1915/1915" type="inclusive">1915</unitdate><unitdate normal="1917/1917" type="inclusive">1917</unitdate><container label="Oversize Folder" type="folder">1</container></did></c04></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_2c9bc59f56c326b832c9077cf6ce4f50" level="file"><did><unittitle>Scrapbook Materials</unittitle><physdesc><extent>8 folders</extent></physdesc><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" normal="1903/1918" type="inclusive">1903-1918</unitdate><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did></c02></c01></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
