<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid>umich-bhl-852085</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Finding aid for Manuel Luis Quezon papers, 1909-1944</titleproper><author>Finding aid created by Isagni R. Medina, National Library, Manila (Filipiniana Division, Quezoniana Section), 1968; further descriptive and analytical details about the collection provided by Michael Cullinane.</author></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Bentley Historical Library</publisher><p><date>2007</date></p></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2022-10-07 12:36:12 -0400</date>.</creation><langusage>The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage><descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules></profiledesc><revisiondesc><change><date>2015-09-15</date><item>Corrected extent</item></change><change><date>2006-01-18</date><item>Original encoding from Word 2000 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change><change><date>2016-11-21</date><item>Updated Conditions Governing Use Note</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader><frontmatter><titlepage><publisher>Bentley Historical Library <lb/>University of Michigan</publisher><titleproper>Finding aid for Manuel Luis Quezon papers, 1909-1944</titleproper><author>Finding aid created by Isagni R. Medina, National Library, Manila (Filipiniana Division, Quezoniana Section), 1968; further descriptive and analytical details about the collection provided by Michael Cullinane.</author></titlepage></frontmatter><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Bentley Historical Library</corpname>
      <extptr actuate="onload" href="bhladd" show="embed"/>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Manuel Luis Quezon papers</unittitle>
    <origination label="creator">
      <persname source="lcnaf">Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944</persname>
    </origination>
    <unitid type="call number">852085 Aa 2</unitid>
    <physdesc>
      <extent>54 microfilms</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate normal="1909/1944" type="inclusive">1909-1944</unitdate>
    <langmaterial id="aspace_a7794ae5b9f0e9edb30b492b86da1f63">The material is in <language encodinganalog="041" langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
    <abstract id="aspace_711851729e695f14245f7a3c4105c10c">President of the Commonwealth of the Philippines, 1935-1944; correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches, articles, and other materials relating to his career, 1909-1944.</abstract>
  </did>
  <descgrp type="admin">
    <acqinfo><p>The microfilming of the papers of Manuel Quezon (donor no. <num encodinganalog="541$e" type="donor">4715</num>) was a joint project of the National Library of the Philippines and the University of Michigan. The agreement was signed in 1967 and the project completed in 1969.</p></acqinfo>
    <accessrestrict><p>The collection is open to research.</p></accessrestrict>
    <userestrict><p>Copyright is not held by the Regents of the University of Michigan. Patrons are responsible for determining the appropriate use or reuse of materials.</p></userestrict>
    <prefercite><p>[item], folder, reel, Manuel Luis Quezon papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>
  </descgrp>
  <bioghist><p>Manuel Luis Quezon (August 19, 1878-August 1, 1944) was born in Baler, Tayabas (now Quezon Province), Philippines. He was the eldest son of Lucio Quezon and Maria Dolores Molina; married Aurora Aragon, December 14, 1918; children, Maria Aurora, Maria Zeneida, and Manuel, Jr. Quezon was educated at the San Juan de Letrán College (B.A., summa cum laude, 1894) and University of Santo Tomás (Ll. B., 1903).</p><p> Provincial fiscal of Mindoro, 1903-1906; Municipal Concilor of Tayabas, Tayabas, 1906 (Resigned to run as governor of Tayabas Province, 1906); Co-founder of the <title render="italic">Partido Independista Inmediata</title> 1906-1907; Governor of Tayabas Province, 1906; First assemblyman from Tayabas to the First Philippine Assembly, 1907; Resident Commissioner of the Philippines to the United States, 1909-1917 (re-elected 1911, 1913, 1915); President of the Senate, 1916-1935; First President of the Commonwealth of the Philippines, 1935-1941; of the Commonwealth government-in-exile (Washington, D.C., U.S.A.), 1941-1944.</p></bioghist>
  <scopecontent><p>The Manuel Quezon microfilm was a joint project of the University of Michigan and the National Library of the Philippines. The resulting 54 reels of microfilm represent the most important, but not all, of the Quezon papers. The papers span the period beginning with Quezon's residence in Washington DC as Resident Commissioner and ending with his death in New York State during World War II. There is no material relating to his public service in Mindoro or Tayabas Province, approximately 1903-1909, or to his education.</p><p> The collection is of greatest importance for the wide range of Quezon's correspondence and for the documentation of the events and politics involved in the long history of the Philippine independence movement. Quezon corresponded widely both with political figures in the United States as well as with the other great leaders within the Philippines.</p><p> Due to the sensitivity of the positions he held, especially before independence, Quezon had cause to devise codes which he used in his correspondence. Staff members of the National Library have prepared a glossary of these words and numerical codes with their meaning. These code indices cover different chronological periods: Code I: 1911-1912; Code II: 1911 and January-July 1914; Code III: 1914-1915 (also known as the War Department code); Code IV: 1917-1929; Code V: 1930s. This code index has been place with the first set of microfilm boxes; a second set has been attached to the printed finding aid.</p><p> The collection has been arranged into three series: General Correspondence; Speeches, Articles, Statements, Reports, Interviews, and Book File; and Correspondents File.</p><p> Many of the documents had suffered physical damage or decay prior to microfilming. Some are fragments of the original and portions of others may be illegible due to staining, water damage or climate induced decay.</p></scopecontent>
  <controlaccess>
    <p>
      <extptr actuate="onload" href="accnote" show="embed"/>
    </p>
    <subject source="lcsh">Lawyers -- Philippines.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.</geogname>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc type="combined"><c01 id="aspace_cc7d111c324a3b30507a1bff8117ebc7" level="series"><did><unittitle>General Correspondence</unittitle><physdesc><extent>21 reels</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1909/1944" type="inclusive">1909-1944</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>General Correspondence (1909-1944; Reels 1-21) consists of letters, telegrams, cablegrams, radiograms, and memoranda sent and received. The papers have been arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by name of correspondent. The series divides into three chronological subseries corresponding to different phases or political responsibilities in Quezon's career. These subseries are: Resident Commissioner of the Philippines to the United States (1909-1916); President of the Senate (1916-1935); and President of the Commonwealth of the Philippines (1935-1944).</p><p> For each subseries a brief, narrative scope and content note provides an overview Quezon's activities and the nature of the correspondence. For each roll, researcher Michael Cullinane has provided a more detailed list of significant topics and correspondents.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_de67a77ff95c2e073a3da9c925351093" level="subseries"><did><unittitle>Resident Commissioner of the Philippines to the United States</unittitle><unitdate normal="1909/1916" type="inclusive">1909-1916</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>The Resident Commissioner of the Philippines to the United States (1909-1916; Reels 1-7) subseries documents Quezon activities while serving in the United States. The papers are of two categories, his interaction with Americans on issues of Philippine independence and his communications with colleagues and other Philippine politicians on events taking place in Manila and elsewhere in the Islands. While serving in the United States, Quezon carried on extensive correspondence with Erwin Winslow and other members of the Anti-Imperialist League and with other individuals supportive of Philippine independence. The papers also indicate Quezon's efforts on behalf of Philippine modernization and economic prosperity as a necessary prerequisite to independence.</p></scopecontent><c03 id="aspace_a6bedc0c49cc3658a12a54b78a507977" level="file"><did><unittitle>Nov. 9, 1909-August 5, 1911</unittitle><container label="Roll" type="reel">1</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 1, Nov. 9, 1909-August 5, 1911, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Extensive correspondence with Erving Winslow (Secretary, Anti-Imperialist League) mostly re: working toward Philippine independence</item><item>Correspondence with various U.S. congressmen, businesses, etc.</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>Sergio Osmeña--extensive correspondence, mostly cablegrams, specifically: <list type="simple"><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Confidential letter in Spanish (Dec. 24, 1910)</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Long letter (March 9, 1911)</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (April 21, 1911)</item></list> </item><item>Jaime de Veyra (kept Quezon informed of events in Manila) <list type="simple"><item>de Veyra to Quezon. Letter. Spanish (Dec. 7, 1910) re: Osmeña's work in Assembly</item><item>de Veyra to Quezon. Letter. Spanish (Feb. 14, 1911)</item><item>de Veyra to Quezon. Letter. Spanish (March 4, 1911)</item></list> </item><item>James Harbord--continual correspondence, usually personal and re: Philippine--American relations</item><item>Harry Hill Bandholtz. Letter (March 23, 1910)</item><item>Teodoro M. Kalaw--some confidential, informative letters to Quezon, especially <list type="simple"><item>letter (Aug. 2, 1911)</item></list> </item><item>Vicente Singson Encarnacion <list type="simple"><item>Singson to Quezon. 2 page letter (April 2, 1911)</item><item>Quezon to Singson. 5 page reply (May 25, 1911)</item></list> </item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_90a4b2184f08e708af6e863e4a9f46a9" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1911-08-05/1912-07-19" type="inclusive">August 5, 1911-July 19, 1912</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">2</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 2, August 5, 1911-July 19, 1912, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Extensive correspondence with Erving Winslow (Anti-Imperialist League)</item><item>James Blount--occasional correspondence, especially <list type="simple"><item>James Blount to Quezon. Letter (May 6, 1912) re: his complaint of Quezon quoting from Blount's as yet unpublished manuscript on Philippine affairs under the U. S.</item><item>James Blount to Quezon. Letter (May 8, 1912) much of same; later Quezon replies</item></list> </item><item>William A. Jones</item><item>Various other U.S. congressmen mostly re: political status of the Philippines</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>Sergio Osmeña--regular heavy correspondence, see especially <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 7 page letter (Aug. 18, 1911). Quezon wants to stay in Washington longer since he's not needed in Philippines until next year to muster votes for party in election.</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (n.d., between late 1911 and early 1912)</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page letter (March 14, 1912)</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 13 page letter (March 27, 1912) plus another related letter from the same time</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 2 page letter (April 13, 1912)</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (June 8, 1912)</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 2 page letter (June 14, 1912)</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (June 15, 1912)</item></list> </item><item>T. Pardo de Tavera (an occasional letter)</item><item>Juan Villamor--interesting letter complaining of corruption in Manila</item><item>T. Kalaw</item><item>J. de Veyra--continual correspondence, especially interesting <list type="simple"><item>de Veyra to Quezon. 5 page letter (May 11, 1912)</item><item>Quezon to de Veyra. Reply (June 20, 1912)</item></list> </item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_a5a26c4c4627eb6f794dd3f12101194a" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1912-07-20/1913-07-14" type="inclusive">July 20, 1912-July 14, 1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">3</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 3, July 20, 1912-July 14, 1913, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Continuing correspondence with Erving Winslow</item><item>James Blount</item><item>Francis Woodruff</item><item>Bishop C. Brent (mostly from Manila)</item><item>Frank McIntyre (Chief, Bureau of Insular Affairs)</item><item>William A. Jones</item><item>Benito Legarda (Resident Commissioner, Washington)</item><item>William M. Shuster (in Philippines and in U. S.). Much correspondence with him beginning in mid-1913 with Quezon maneuvering to have him appointed next Governor-General to follow Forbes.</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>S. Osmeña--letters, cables, etc.--mostly concerning Philippine-U.S. relations, Philippine political maneuvering in Manila by Osmeña and by Quezon in Washington with respect to Philippine independence, some on Partido Nacioanalista, etc</item><item>J. de Veyra</item><item>T. Pardo de Tavera</item><item>T. Kalaw</item><item>James Ross--regular friendly, mostly personal correspondence with occasional discussions of Philippine affairs and problems</item><item>Newton W. Gilbert (Acting Governor-General)--official correspondence</item></list></item><item>Other <list type="simple"><item>M. Kalaw's correspondence with Erwin Winslow, U.S. Congressmen, etc.--while Quezon was in Manila (late 1912 to early 1913)</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_9c3e505073e33c376aecd513b13cafd4" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1913-07-21/1914-06-29" type="inclusive">July 21, 1913-June 29, 1914</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">4</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 4, July 21, 1913-June 29, 1914, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Correspondence with Erwin Winslow, also M. Kalaw's correspondence with Erwin Winslow in Quezon's absence</item><item>Moorfield Storey--more frequent correspondence</item><item>William Shuster--mostly re: effort to get him appointed Governor-General and his work as a lawyer for Renacimiento</item><item>Frank McIntyre</item><item>H. Parker Willis (Prof. in New York)</item><item>Charles Miller (Editorial Staff, New York Times)--especially interesting: <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to Miller. Letters (March 19, 1914 and March 20, 1914) re: Quezon's defense of Philippine and refutation of Worcester, esp. his "Slavery" book (a big concern of Quezon)</item></list> </item><item>Numerous letters of other Americans (congressmen, businessmen, newsmen, etc.) to gain public and legislative support for Jones Bill</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>T. Pardo de Tavera</item><item>T. Kalaw</item><item>V. Singson Encarnacion</item><item>Two reports by Governor-General Forbes prior to his departure from Philippines re: state of peace throughout the Philippines--especially Aug. 25, 1913 report in which he expresses a concern that maybe Quezon is being given too big a hand in Philippine affairs and in Washington decision making</item><item>Sergio Osmeña, heavy correspondence, especially interesting: <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (Aug. 26, 1913) re: Quezon's accompanying Harrison to Manila</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Aug. 30, 1913) re: his desire to have a Philippine Vice-Governor, and that all pro-Republicans would not agree to this</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Dec. 31, 1913) re: getting Shuster a commission appointment</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 3 page letter (Jan. 20, 1914)</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 4 page letter (June 17, 1914) re: Jones Bill, and much other 1914 correspondence to get bill through U.S. Congress their way and in their form, attempt to expand legislative powers, create new powers for Philippines in all branches.</item></list> </item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_014aa7d1031d107c8f8eea65a4e64b0a" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1914-06-30/1914-11-09" type="inclusive">June 30, 1914-November 9, 1914</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">5</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 5, June 30, 1914-November 9, 1914, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Continuing correspondence with Erwin Winslow</item><item>Frank McIntyre</item><item>Moorfield Storey</item><item>H. Parker Willis</item><item>W. A. Jones</item><item>W. M. Shuster</item><item>Senator R. F. Pettigrew</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>F. B. Harrison</item><item>James Ross</item><item>V. Singson Encarnacion, especially Quezon to Singson (Aug. 1, 1914) re: Quezon's explanation to him of his activities in Washington and fixing independence date</item><item>F. Buencamino, Jr., especially his two letters to Quezon (Aug. 24, 28, 1914) re: his report to Quezon on the Manila situation upon his return there</item><item>T. Kalaw, especially Kalaw to Quezon (Sept. 24, 1914) re: mostly Manila politics</item><item>Assembly (Justo, Filemon and Lopez). Letter (Oct. 24, 1914) praising Quezon's good work for the Philippines</item><item>Sergio Osmeña, especially correspondence dealing with Jones Bill, independence and Manila affairs <list type="simple"><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (July 6, 1914) re: a mass meeting by the opposition parties in Manila</item><item>Quezon to Mariano Lim, Sandiko and Sumulong. Letter drafts (July) 1914 re: his reactions to the meeting in Manila (noted above) expressing his criticism of their action</item><item>Lim, Sandiko and Sumulong to Quezon. Cable (July 13, 1914) re: their explanation, saying they had not cabled him their desires because Quezon had already pursued the goal they sought, a specific date for independence to be in Jones Bill</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (July 14, 1914) re: introduction of Jones Bill to Congress, calming effect in Manila politics</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (July 15, 1914) expresses the pro-nationalism sentiment of pro-Jones U. S. Congress N.P. they say really represents people and N.P. will be main group responsible for implementing its politics</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Letter 12 pages (Oct. 29, 1914) re: most Jones Bill</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Letter 7 pages (Nov. 5, 1914) re: events and personalities in Manila</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Letter 5 pages (Nov. 9, 1914)</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Letter (Aug. 30, 1914) re: disagreement between Harrison and Riggs</item></list> </item><item>de Veyra <list type="simple"><item>de Veyra to Quezon. Letter (July 1, 1914)--notes about Denison (new Secretary of Interior): "es un Worcester en Reves"</item><item>de Veyra to Quezon. 15 page letter (Sept. 10, 1914). He describes for Quezon's knowledge each of the new Democratic administrators in the Philippine Government: Harrison, Martin, Riggs, Denison</item><item>de Veyra to Quezon. Letter (Sept. 16, 1914) re: more on Riggs, plus a resolution by the "Junta Recaudadora..."</item><item>de Veyra to Quezon. 13 page letter (Sept. 21, 1914) re: Manila affairs</item></list> </item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_37a54b4b8dcf68ea094826661045e350" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1914-11-11/1916-03-25" type="inclusive">November 11, 1914-March 25, 1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">6</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 6, November 11, 1914-March 25, 1916, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Erwin Winslow</item><item>Frank McIntyre</item><item>Moorfield Storey</item><item>James Blount--who offers to make replies to Worcester's accusation, Quezon tells him he will do it himself</item><item>Woodrow Wilson</item><item>Numerous U.S. congressmen re. Jones Bill</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>Secretary Denison</item><item>F. B. Harrison</item><item>Lope K. Santos (especially Feb. 22, 1916)</item><item>V. Singson Encarnacion (especially Jan. 20, 1915) re: Jones Bill</item><item>T. Pardo de Tavera, especially letter, Quezon to Pardo de Tavera, Nov. 10, 1915, where Quezon notes: "Yo estoy convencido que [Worcester] es un hombre que tiene muy poco respecto a ca verdad."</item><item>Sergio Osmeña (heavy correspondence), particularly: <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 7 page letter (Nov. 11, 1914)</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Dec. 8, 1914) re: Sixto Lopez affair and notes: "Coming from certain towns Bulacan, I think Nac. Party are now in control there." [Sandiko's Prov] - Quezon replies to this letter, Dec. 11, 1914</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Dec. 11, 1914)--notes that they are keeping Secretary Denison quiet during sensitive debate on Jones Bill in Washington</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Dec. 15. 1914) re: their strong mutual loyalty and Harrison</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 5 page letter (Dec. 18, 1914) thanks Osmeña for his praise, and praises Osmeña in turn</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Dec. 19, 1914)--suggests redistributing Senate districts, speaks of balancing off provinces with others politically</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Dec. 21, 1914)--suggests no need to redistrict, too difficult</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 4, 1915) re: "uprising" Navotas, Rizal and incapable government of Rizal</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Jan. 4, 1915)--suggesting that if Gov. Rizal is incompetent, he should have him removed</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 8, 1915) re: military intervention (esp. Harrison's failure to act)</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Feb. 8, 1915) re: how to handle above situation</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 23, 1915)--above satisfactorily handled by Harrison</item><item>Heavy correspondence re: Clarke amendment May 1915-Feb. 1916 Osmeña wants Phil. Assembly's independence bill with date to be considered before Clarke amendment, in Jan. 1916, Phil. Assembly finally endorses Clarke amendment</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 26, 1916) re: Sandiko's effort to get together with Sen. Clarke and Democratic party in Washington</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 28, 1916) "Sandiko Party are claiming Clarke amendment as their own"</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Jan. 28, 1916) re: his proof that Clarke amendment was his baby, and he works with Clarke on it</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 30, 1916) Reports that Sandiko meeting celebrating their pretended victory because of the Clarke amendment was held this morning without any consequence</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 5, 1916) re: another opposition meeting and resolution</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Feb. 5, 1916) calm among opposition</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 8, 1916) re: conservative Philippine opinion of Clarke amendment, also re: Sandiko and Sumulong activities</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 11, 1916) re: some opposition guarantees to moderate their behavior</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 13, 1916) "...nobody knows here the inside of the Jones Bill situation. The information is not necessary but may be convenient and will use it as circumstances warrant." [re: earlier Quezon to Osmeña cable on Jones]</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Feb. 15, 1916) "...I think would be good idea to have Singson and Sandiko recommend neutralization..."</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 25, 1916) re: inability to get local resolutions, etc. in support of Clarke amendments, suggests that Sandiko's pro-Clarke activities may have deterred many from endorsing the amendment</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable from Cebu (March 7, 1916) "There are some movements among the progresistas in Iloilo against Clarke amendment..." [but Osmeña notes that Nacionalistas there held a "mass meeting" in support of the amendment]</item></list> </item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_9930fa0cf47e134a70e749bb5f4b45eb" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1916-03-25/1916-10-15" type="inclusive">March 25, 1916-October 15, 1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">7</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 7 (part), March 25, 1916-October 15, 1916, with notes and comments by Michael Culliane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Erwin Winslow</item><item>W. M. Shuster (now returned to U.S.)</item><item>James Long</item><item>James Ross (now in U.S.)</item><item>Mr. Stone re: building sugar mills in Negros</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>T. Pardo de Tavera</item><item>F. B. Harrison</item><item>Harold M. Pitt (President, Manila Merchants' Association)</item><item>Vincente Sotto, esp: Quezon to Sotto. Letter [in response to a letter from Sotto accusing Quezon of making contradicting statements]--Quezon defends himself, stresses that any seeming contradictions are changes in form, not content</item><item>de Veyra to Quezon, some letters concern "grave crisis" facing hemp</item><item>Sergio Osmeña (heavy correspondence): <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (March 29, 1916)--inquiring as to truth of rumors about wealthy in Iloilo being opposed to Clarke amendment in newspaper</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (March 30, 1916) "...there is no truth in report published and Harrison cabled accordingly, statement will be given out tomorrow after fresh information from Iloilo, Occid. Neg secured."</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 11, 1916) quotes endorsement of Clarke amendment by people of Iloilo and Negros Occidental</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 22, 1916) re: above (Iloilo)</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 27, 1916) long note clearing up above affair</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (May 2, 1916) re: defeat of Clarke amendment in Congress</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (July 17, 1916) re: suggested new political leaders</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (July 17, 1916) re: his desire to offer government positions to Justo Lukew and Gregorio Nieva [presumably for faithful party service]</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (October 4, 1916) re: congratulations for "grandiose" Nacionalista victory led by Osmeña</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (June 13, 1917) re: Worcester and Visayas Refining Co.</item></list> </item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_94896f7f7bce410886f33e8539a8dfb1" level="subseries"><did><unittitle>President of the Senate</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>The President of the Senate (1916-1935; Reels 7-18) subseries details the evolution of the Philippine government with the filling of positions by Philippine nationals and his increasingly difficult relationship with speaker of the Philippine Assembly Sergio Osmeña for control of the legislature and the Nacionalista party. There is continuing documentation of the relationship between the Philippines and the United States with the drafting of legislation in the United States leading to independence, first the Hare-Hawes-Cutting Act (which was reject by the Philippine legislature), then the Tydings-McDuffie Act which passed.</p></scopecontent><c03 id="aspace_de34ddf1ddd2b992c23db0073dc3729f" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1916-10-16/1918-02-15" type="inclusive">October 16, 1916-February 15, 1918</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">7</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 7, October 16, 1916-February 15, 1918, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (June 18, 1917) re. Worcester and Visayas Refining Co.</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (August 7, 1917)--more of Worcester and Visayas Refining Co., plus he expresses dissatisfaction with Nieva' s review</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (August 8, 1917) "...referring to Nieva, I think very important we have our own printing plant, that could publish newspaper and magazine. If you approve idea I shall buy press and linotypes. Yangco and Fernandez can fix it."</item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_838057c02a70e67c2baddfc9c6da7544" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1918-02-21/1919-04-01" type="inclusive">February 21, 1918-April 1, 1919</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">8</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 8, February 21, 1918-April 1, 1919, with notes and comments prepared by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Erwin Winslow--much less now with Quezon in Philippines</item><item>F. McIntyre</item><item>Charles M. Yeater</item><item>General Walcutt</item><item>Rafferty (San Francisco)</item><item>J. de Veyra and Yangco (Resident Commissioners.) - extensive correspondence, especially with de Veyra re: business (i.e. hemp prices, setting up business in Philippines, etc.), some also relate to integration of Philippine National Guard into U.S. Federal Service</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>V. Madrigal (Madrigal and Co., Manila) mostly re: building up sugar industry, includes charts, etc. (late 1918)</item><item>C. A. Fernandez (Negros)--re: sugar centrals in Bais, Tanjay, LaCarlota--some details concerning town and their haciendas (esp. September 28, 1918)</item><item>"Confidential memorandum for Governor-General" by Osmeña and Quezon (November 19, 1918)--mostly re: business and agriculture in Philippines.</item><item>Sergo Osmeña (much correspondence): <list type="simple"><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Letter (Feb. 21, 1918) re: a commemoration for deceased Antonio</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (May 19, 1918) re: acquiring competing coconut industry in Cebu</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (June 17, 1918) N.P.'s nominating procedure</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (June 21, 1918)--gives his o.k.</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable [rush to Cebu] (Sept.9, 1918) re: sadness in Osmeña family</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Sept. 10, 1918) re: Osmeña reply to Quezon sympathy</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Sept. 19, 1918) re: Singson's "turncoating"</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Sept. 24, 1918) re: his reply to above Osmeña to Quezon.</item><item>Cable to Washington (Feb. 3, 1919) "Minority party is endeavoring to have legislation pass a repel asking the U.S. and allied powers to grant Philippines a seat at the peace conference. Please cable at once what we can say and what we cannot say on this matter."</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Feb. 4, 1919) re:"..Harrison is as strong as ever with U.S..."</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Feb. 5, 1919) re: his help of D. Jakosauen</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (March 26, 1919) re: cutting size of independence mission and at same time trying to avoid the cropping up of "jealousies, envies and resentments of members..."</item></list> </item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_93d69eabc879cceefb2c690735dc4b4f" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1919-04-01/1921-01-05" type="inclusive">April 1, 1919-January 5, 1921</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">9</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 9, April 1, 1919-January 5, 1921, with comments and notes by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Erwin Winslow--greatly decreased</item><item>Camilo Osias--occasional, mostly re: Philippine independence activities</item><item>George Malcolm</item><item>J. de Veyra and Yangco (Resident Commissioner)--mostly re: business, "coastline laws", independence issue, continual advice being given by Quezon</item><item>I. Gabaldon (later joins de Veyra as Resident Commissioner)</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>E. Aguinaldo (Oct. 27, 1919)</item><item>Manuel Quiogue (Officer of Census) esp. 5 page letter (July 10, 1920) re: a complaint filed with Quezon presumably involving Julio de la Rosa</item><item>Sergio Osmeña--somewhat reduced in number, include one instance of a near rift between them: <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to Osmeña (from Washington). Cable (April 3, 1919) with Quezon complaining that his advice is no longer being heeded as before</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 5, 1919) Osmeña denies it, suggests it must be Quezon's bad health that causes his unexplainable behavior, he expresses ignorance of Quezon's motives</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 5, 1919) re: a confusion in their communication procedure, which explains Osmeña's confusion about Quezon's motives, etc.--recommends a more efficient system of citing cablegrams</item></list> </item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_b9e1a3c470df8659abddba5614b6e2dd" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1921-01-06/1922-05-24" type="inclusive">January 6, 1921-May 24, 1922</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">10</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 10, January 6, 1921-May 24, 1922, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>James A. Frear (Pro-Filipino, U.S. Representative)</item><item>Judge Horace M. Towner (U.S. Representative)</item><item>F. M. McIntyre</item><item>General J. Harbord--containing personal correspondence</item><item>James J. Rafferty (Philippine Commercial Agent, S.F.) --mostly re: the status of Filipinos in the U.S.</item><item>F.B.Harrison, esp. Harrison to Quezon letter (Nov. 7, 1921) re: (in part) D. Barrows</item><item>General H. H. Bandholtz, Quezon met with him in Washington</item><item>Charles E. Russell, author and publisher (journalist?)</item><item>J. de Veyra (Resid. Comm.) quite heavy, much re: selection of Governor-General and Wood <list type="simple"><item>de Veyra to Quezon and Osmeña. 5 page letter (Jan. 15, 1921)</item><item>Osmeña and Quezon to de Veyra. Cable (Jan. 18, 1921) re: evaluation of Wood, generally opposed to his "military" character, contends "people" will react negatively to this aspect of Wood, as like in Spanish days</item><item>de Veyra to Osmeña. Cable (Jan. 20, 1921) re: Wood: "Believe, however, that the objective to his candidacy is more apparent than real..."; warns that the choice could be worse</item><item>de Veyra to Osmeña and Quezon. 4 page letter (Feb. 15, 1921) re: Wood plus four letters that de Veyra sent to Wood (February, early April, 1921)</item><item>de Veyra to Osmeña and Quezon. Cable (Feb. 25, 1921) Re: Wood "...knowing his simplicity, sincerity and uprightness I can draw nothing from his attitude but a spirit of good will towards us and our aspirations." (written after a meeting de Veyra had with Wood)</item><item>correspondence re: Wood continues, with also heavy correspondence re: Wood-Forbes Mission--through 1921-1922</item><item>de Veyra to Quezon. Letters (during June, 1921) re: various attacks against Quezon in U.S. due to his alleged contradictory public and private position re: Philippine independence and also the changing mood in U.S.</item><item>Osmeña to de Veyra. Cable (Aug. 3, 1921) Osmeña recommends N. Romualdez (Leyte) to be chief justice, Philippine Supreme Court (again on Aug.6, 1921) --gives praise</item><item>Osmeña to de Veyra. Cable (Aug. 11, 1921) "to avoid further complications" Osmeña received the immediate appointment of Arraullo to be chief justice-can't get Romualdez</item></list> </item><item>Isauro Gabaldon (Resident Commissioner) esp: <list type="simple"><item>Gabaldon to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 13, 1922) re: Quezon break with Osmeña</item><item>Quezon to Gabaldon. Cable (Jan. 23, 1922) Quezon's reply on above</item></list> </item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>F. Buencamino, esp. 3 page letter to "My Dear Casey" re: his suggestions for new Philippines</item><item>R. Palma. Letter (Nov. 9, 1921) from Quezon--re: political situation</item><item>T. Sandiko (Letter to F. B. Harrison--Feb. 8, 1921) plus note written on it to Quezon, compelling Quezon to look with favor upon Sandiko's resolution re: electoral Law-- thus Sandiko's letter plus Harrison's comment forwarded to Quezon</item><item>Henry D. Woolfe. (Letter to Quezon, April 21, 1922--re: complaints)</item><item>Mariano R. Marcos (Ladag, Ilocos Sur) re: general conditions in his province in election (April 8, 1922)</item><item>R. Montinola--mostly re: getting him to defect to Coleonvistas, esp. <list type="simple"><item>J. Ross to R. M. 4 page letter (Jan. 25, 1922) Ross praises Quezon, suggest R.M. get together with him</item><item>R. M. to J. Ross. Letter (Jan. 31, 1922) R. M.'s response, guarded compliance</item><item>R. M. to Quezon. Letter (Feb. 21, 1922) re: advice to Quezon on Negros politics</item><item>R. M. to Quezon. Letter (Feb. 21, 1922) re: Iloilo politics, esp. Yulo to Roxas to Osmeña</item></list> </item><item>E. Finley Johnson (Associate Justice, Philippine Supreme Court). 2 page letter from Quezon (April 23, 1921) re: Harrison's favoring Nacionalistas, a reply to Johnson</item><item>E. Tirona (Pres. Gen, P. Democrata), esp: <list type="simple"><item>E. T. to Osmeña. 2 page letter (April 30, 1921) re: Democrata real desire for independence</item><item>Osmeña to E. T. 3 page letter (May 3, 1921) re: Nacionalistas policy, suggests a joint petition to the Wood-Forbes mission</item><item>E. T. to Osmeña. Letter (May 4, 1921) re: their mutual desire to form a joint petition, suggests going ahead with it</item></list> </item><item>Elpidio Quirino, esp.: <list type="simple"><item>"Memorandum for the President of the Colect. Party" (March 22, 1922)--to Quezon re: his candidacy in Ilocos Sur and some Colectivista problems in that province</item><item>"Memorandum for Mr. E. Quirino"(March 22, 1922)--from Quezon in response to E. Quirino, also re: strategy in Ilocos Sur and Colectivista action there</item></list> </item><item>[unsigned?) Letter to Quezon (in Tagalog, the first one in the General Correspondence) (March 9, 1921) re: the writers strong desire for Filipino freedom, the Wood-Forbes, a brief review of American period, and he concludes with: "Nais ko pong makita ans ating Kalayaan."</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_9b83f1be6e0ceb9f9fbc40bdceb7bb98" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1922-06-08/1925-06-27" type="inclusive">June 8, 1922-June 27, 1925</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">11</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 11, June 8, 1922-June 27, 1925, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Moorfield Storey</item><item>Harold M. Pitt (Oakland, California) --business</item><item>General H. H. Bandholtz? --mostly all personal</item><item>F. B. Harrison</item><item>James Ross</item><item>Clyde H. Tavenner (editor and publisher of The Philippine Reporter in U.S.)</item><item>Jay Lovestone (Workers Party of America)</item><item>Maximo M. Kalaw--studying and writing in U.S., re: mostly Philippine Party system</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>Camilo Osias, esp. <list type="simple"><item>Four page letter to Quezon (June 15, 1922) re: political situation in Philippines</item><item>Osias to Enage. Memorandum (June 23, 1922) re: his opposition to government funding of Aguinaldo's trip to U.S. (Spanish-American War Veterans Convention)--also refers to a dinner at P. Ostavera's house</item></list> </item><item>Enage--regular correspondence while Quezon in Washington <list type="simple"><item>Enage to Quezon. Cable (June 20, 1922) re: Manila politics, fusion with Democratas, notes: "...Gomez has already declared Colectivista in a banquet in Tacloban...", also expresses desire to get Isagelo de los Santes to affiliate with them</item><item>Enage to Quezon. Cable (Sept. 23, 1924) re: again activities in Manila, report</item></list> </item><item>Isbelo de los Santos, esp: [from Ilocos Sur] <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to Santos (2 page letter), June 21, 1922, in which he moves to get his support</item><item>Santos to Enage. Letter (June 24, 1922) re: favorable response to Quezon's letter</item><item>Quezon to Santos. Letter (June 26, 1922) thanking him for affiliating [other correspondence explaining the role played by Bishop Aglipay in getting Santos to come]</item></list> </item><item>Manuel Quioque. 6 page memo to Quezon (June 24, 1922) re: election</item><item>T. H. Pardo de Tavera. Letter from Quezon (June 26, 1922) re: Philippine and Manila politics</item><item>Jaime C. de Veyra. 3 page letter to Quezon (July 23, 1922)--informing Quezon, who is returning to Manila, of political situation and also an article in La Vanguardia about Democrata victories (June 13) which Veyra believes was written by an important public figure, also briefly re: Wood's stand on the election</item><item>T. Earnshaw. 5 page letter to Quezon (as "Chico"), Aug. 2, 1922 re: fusion, his opinion</item><item>Fermin Torralba (Bohol). 2 page letter to Quezon (March 11, 1924) re: his loyalty to Quezon, but his opposition to Osmeña, thus again fusion</item><item>E. Aguinaldo, mostly re: his mission to U.S. (March-April, 1924)</item><item>Manuel Roxas, heavy correspondence with Quezon while Quezon and Osmeña were not yet in Washington--mostly re: Fairfield Bill--also heavy correspondence Washington to Manila from Quezon and Osmeña when they arrive in Washington</item><item>I. Gabaldon. Cable from Quezon to Washington, (Nov. 28, 1924) re: Quezon's advice to Gabaldon to either return and campaign for representative or drop out of campaign in Nueva Ecija in order not to "expose yourself to a defeat"</item><item>Vicente Bunuan, heavy correspondence with Quezon from Washington as head of Philippine Press. Letter, March 14, 1925, refers to reports in U.S. re: a class war going on in Nueva Ecija led by Colorums and Politices</item><item>M. J. Cuenco (Cebu), esp. Cuenco to Roxas. 11 page letter (Dec. 6, 1922) re: Osmeña</item><item>M. M. Kalaw, esp. Quezon to Kalaw. Letter (Nov. 19, 1923) re: Quezon negative reaction to Kalaw's attack on him for favoring Nacs. as appointees</item><item>Roberto Alcantara (Democrata), esp. letter to Quezon (Nov. 22, 1923) re: his praise of Quezon for including opposition party members in his appointments</item><item>S. Osmeña, esp. 2 page letter from Quezon (June 17, 1925) re: the arrangements of a mass triumphant rally and celebration in Manila including Osmeña, Quezon, Roxas, etc. Quezon laments that victorious Cebu legislators will not be coming for this, he advises that they change their plans and come earlier</item><item>Governor-General Leonard Wood, esp: <list type="simple"><item>[unsigned] to Wood. 3 page letter (June 3, 1924) re: Quezon's work in Washington and progress of Fairfield Bill and setting a date for independence</item><item>Quezon to Wood. Letter (July 3, 1923) re: a warning to him concerning the Filipino attitude toward him</item><item>Quezon, Roxas, Laurel, et. al to Wood. Letters of resignation (July 17, 1923)</item><item>Quezon to Wood. Letter (July 19, 1923) stressing the peaceful nature of their move, no need to call army or be alarmed</item></list> </item><item>Quezon to [Minamahal na Kababayan?]--brief letter in Tagalog by Quezon (Oct. 4, 1923) re: the running of Ramon Fernandez for Guevara's seat in Senate [1st letter in general correspondence written by Quezon in Tagalog]</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_eae08f6d4f2917ccc43feb2591a62e40" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1925-07-03/1928-02-11" type="inclusive">July 3, 1925-February 11, 1928</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">12</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 12, July 3, 1925-February 11, 1928, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>F. McIntyre, Moorfield Storey, Frank Carpenter, Carmi A. Thompson</item><item>Secretary of War</item><item>Governor-General Henry L. Stimson--heavy in late 1927, early 1928, much re: getting him settled in</item><item>James Harbord and James Ross--continuing personal correspondence; Harbord to Secretary of War (Oct. 13, 1927) with lavish praise of Quezon</item><item>F. B. Harrison</item><item>W. H. Lawrence (Attorney, S.F. California)</item><item>Many U.S. Congressmen, esp. Sen. William King and Sen. Burton Wheeler</item><item>Jose Abad Santos (Philippine Press, Washington) "My Dear Joe"</item><item>V. Bunuan (Philippine Press) re: independence issue and activities in Washington</item><item>Pedro Guevara (Resid. Comm.) much re: reorganization of Filipino movement, and U.S. Congressional activities, etc.</item><item>Clyde Tavenner (The Philippine Republic) esp.: <list type="simple"><item>C.T. to Recto. Letter (July 3, 1926) re: a very anti-Osmeña attack, esp. of Osmeña's "no agitation" policy, C.T. wants more radical moves</item><item>Quezon to Tavenner. Letter (Dec. 15, 1927) re: removal of support from Philippine Republic and expressing animosity to C. T. for his threats, etc., breaking their friendship</item></list> </item><item>MacArthur, esp. letter from Quezon (Dec. 25, 1925), personal, but also re: sad condition in Philippines at time</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>Benigno Aquino (Maj. Floor Leader, House)</item><item>R. Palma</item><item>James Ross, esp. letter from Quezon (Jan. 21, 1928) re: Stimson's settling in, stress that Mrs. Stimson "must be made to meet the right kind of American ladies in the Philippines" [i.e. Mrs. Ross and her friends]</item><item>S. Osmeña (in Washington) esp: <list type="simple"><item>Letter to his legislative colleagues, 25 pages (Sept. 3, 1926) re: Washington activities</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Nov. 3, 1925) re: selection of Resid. Comm.</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Nov. 4, 1925) "regarding myself, leave matter entirely to you and party"</item></list> </item><item>E. T. Tirona, esp: <list type="simple"><item>Tirona [Gov.] Letter (July 22, 1926) re: planned demonstration to Thompson Mission</item><item>Quezon to Tirona. Letter (July 29, 1926)</item><item>Tirona to Quezon. Letter (Aug. 3, 1926) Quezon tells Tirona of Thomas Gumez (Democrata)'s seat in Senate vacant, Tirona tells Quezon Democrata will not be putting up candidate to fill it</item></list> </item><item>Leonard Wood, esp. Executive Order (Nov. 9, 1926) abolishing Board of Control</item><item>Montinola (Gov. Iloilo) (Pres. Democratas), esp: <list type="simple"><item>Montinola to Quezon. Letter and enclosure (Feb. 21, 1927) re: suggestion unites front</item><item>Quezon to Montinola. Letter (March 22, 1927)--most favorable reply</item></list> </item><item>Tomas Confesor (Representative, House), esp. letter to Quezon and reply by Quezon (early Nov., 1927) re: his split with Roxas, Quezon advises getting back together against opposition</item><item>National Supreme Council, esp.: <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to N.S.C. (Sept. 22, 1926) re: effort and problem of getting a united Filipino stand on big issues, Quezon cautions: "...soy de opinion que el momento no permite que en la expresion de muestras aspiraliones se use de un lenguate que pueda dar lugar a una deble interpretacion."</item></list> </item><item>Committee of Independence, esp. letter of Quezon to Committee (Sept. 26, 1926) re: reactivation of its activities and work for Filipino independence</item><item>Maximo Kalaw, esp.: <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to Kalaw. 3 page letter (Sept. 20, 1927) re: Kalaw's joint stand with Sumulong on Independence Fund Drive, opposed to it, Quezon explains his side</item><item>Kalaw to Quezon. 3 page letter (Sept. 26, 1927) re: a frank refutation of Quezon's argument, says he'll publish more articles re: Filipino parties, esp. Filipino party system</item></list> </item><item>Manuel Roxas, esp: <list type="simple"><item>Roxas to Quezon. 4 page letter (May 27, 1927) re: a political description of politics on Capiz and Nacionalista power there, also Ledesma's power</item><item>Roxas to Quezon. Cable (June 22-23, 1927) re: successful election results Capiz, Romblon, and Cebu</item><item>Quezon to Roxas. Letter (Jan. 23, 1928) re: Stimson's settling in "...try to have our people meet the Stimson's socially. You notice he will make it a point to be in touch with us. Have Trining [Mrs. Roxas] and her friends call on Mrs. Stimson."</item><item>Quezon to Roxas. Cable (Feb. 1, 1928) re: Stimson socially: "Unlike Wood, he and wife desire to have social intercourse with our people and we should give them opportunity."</item></list> </item><item>[Some correspondence in 1927-28, after Wood's death to get a favorable Governor-General and achieve, "harmony" in government. --Quezon's first choice is McIntyre but is happy with Stimson]</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_6d80bd948c0e281f36bccd8fdf28fbac" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1928-02-11/1929-12-14" type="inclusive">February 11, 1928-December 14, 1929</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">13</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 13, February 11, 1928-December 14, 1929, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane:</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>J. Ross, F. McIntyre, J. Harbord--continuing correspondence</item><item>N. Roosevelt (New York Times)--Quezon takes exception with one of his articles</item><item>V. Bunuan (Philippine Press--heavy correspondence)</item><item>P. Guevara and I. Gabaldon--mostly re: tactics in U.S. Congress</item><item>Guevara to Quezon. Letter (April 17, 1928) re: the controversy caused by Garaldon upon his return to Manila</item><item>Many U.S. Congressmen re: independence issue, campaign in the U.S.</item><item>Henry Stimson (after his departure from Philippines), esp: <list type="simple"><item>Stimson to Quezon. Letter (March 3, 1929) re: controversy over Judge Opisso (Capiz); Henry Stimson favors his promotion in judiciary system, informs Quezon</item><item>Quezon to Stimson. Letter (June 9, 1929)--Quezon examines opposition to Opisso, late reply</item><item>Stimson to Quezon. 4 page letter (July 31, 1929)--gives his case for Opisso, notes that this matter is the "only subject" on which they have disagreed</item></list> </item><item>M. Roxas, esp. letter from Quezon (April 12, 1929) re: judiciary appointments and inner Nacionalista Party feuds, esp. in 2nd district Luzon election, about who is to be speaker pro tem.</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>Henry Stimson</item><item>Philippine Sugar Association--considerable correspondence re: sugar negotiations</item><item>Rafael Alunan (Secretary of Agriculture and National Resources)--also to Washington</item><item>Maximo Kalaw--mostly re: K's attacks on Quezon for work on Jones Bill</item><item>Manuel Roxas, esp.: <list type="simple"><item>Roxas to Quezon. Cable (April 14, 1928) "Gabaldon arrived making statements attacking you, Osmeña, for disloyalty immediate independence laws and cooperation with Stimson, stating further: "In America, they worked only for their personal interests, while I struggled for those of our people." "If there has been treason, they have committed it." Strong statement from you necessary</item><item>Quezon to Roxas. Cable (April 14, 1928) "Not care to answer Gabaldon. Osmeña can do it. His attack is my deserved punishment for having supported a useless public official." See also Quezon to Gabaldon letter (April, 1928)</item></list> </item><item>Louis J. van Schaick, esp.: letter to Quezon plus enclosures (June 5, 1929) re: his memoirs of Quezon</item><item>"Memorandum Para El Senador Osmeña" by Quezon (Sept. 20, 1929) re: the disposition of their official correspondence re: the early campaign in Washington about Jones Bill</item><item>MacArthur, Douglas esp: <list type="simple"><item>MacArthur to Quezon. Letter (March 29, 1929) re: Quezon's and MacArthur's efforts to make MacArthur the new Governor-General after Stimson, a mutual desire</item><item>MacArthur to Quezon. Letter (April 30, 1929) re: above [apparently this whole plan is unknown to Osmeña and Roxas who are in Washington, seemingly working to keep all military people out of Governor-Generalship--their correspondence to Quezon stress Filipino opposition to military pro-consul]</item><item>MacArthur to Quezon. Letter (May 16, 1929) thanking Quezon for his efforts and his loyalty in his behalf, i.e. to get MacArthur into Governor-Generalship</item></list> </item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_d1184d49c39a50bcf4512945e1eb38f8" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1929-12-16/1931-07-24" type="inclusive">December 16, 1929-July 24, 1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">14</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 14, December 16, 1929-July 24, 1931, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>J. Harbord</item><item>H. L. Stimson</item><item>Senator Hawes</item><item>F. McIntyre</item><item>F. B. Harrison</item><item>F. LeJ. Parker (Chief of Bureau Internal Affairs)</item><item>P. J. Hurley (Secretary of War)</item><item>V. Bunuan (much)</item><item>M. Roxas</item><item>John Switzer (New York) re: immigration of Filipinos</item><item>Many Senators and Representatives of U.S. Congress re: Philippine Independence bills, etc.</item><item>Oscar Sutro (California) a 13 page letter to Quezon (Nov. 6, 1930) re: Philippine independence issue, etc.</item><item>Sumulong, Roxas, Briones, Guevara, Osias (Washington) to Quezon, Osmeña, Alas (Manila) (during May, 1930) re: mostly Hawes-Cutting Bill</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>R. Palma</item><item>J. Laurel</item><item>Representative Jose G. Sanvictores (Agusan-Bukidnon)</item><item>Jake Rosenthal (Rosenthal, Inc.--the Rosenthal Shoe Distributor) --a"weekly letter" both informative and interesting and witty re: events especially in Manila to Quezon with "he is recuperating in California (mostly 1931)</item><item>S. Osmeña, esp.: <list type="simple"><item>Osmeña to Quezon. 5 page letter (Dec. 21, 1929) re: final settlement in Philippine Legislature of a meeting between M. Kalaw and Aguinaldo--Osmeña concerned about keeping Aguinaldo on their side --also re: Gabaldon's efforts to get Agoncillo to come over to his side, again Osmeña concerned</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page letter (Dec. 29, 1929) re: a speech he gave in Cebu and support for them there</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. 2 page letter (Dec. 28, 1929) re: plans for "Junta Consoltina" (Advisory Council)</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Letter (Jan.4, 1930) Quezon very sick, advises Osmeña to carry out appointments to "Junta" on his own</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. 4 page letter (Jan. 15, 1930) re: problems facing "Junta" especially with Democratas</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page letter (Jan. 17, 1930) re: more of same ("Advisory Council")</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Letter (Jan. 20, 1930) re: same above</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page letter (Jan. 25, 1930) re: Advisory Council negotiations, Osmeña trying to determine what Quezon really desires, seeking certification</item></list> </item><item>Quezon, Osmeña, Alas to Roxas (Washington. Cable (July 12, 1930) "Nicholas Roosevelt has been mentioned as a candidate for Vice-Governor. Our people are strongly opposed to this appointment."</item><item>Quezon to Governor-General Davis. Letter (July 13, 1930) re: his opposition to Roosevelt</item><item>N. Roosevelt to President of U.S. Letter of resignation (Sept. 24, 1930) also re: his negative opinion of Filipino leaders and their exploits</item><item>Sumulong to Tirona. Cable (July 24, 1930) re: Quezon's undermining of the Independence campaign and his position (actually a misunderstanding)</item><item>Bunuan to Quezon. Letter (Aug. 28, 1930) re: among other things a transmitting of cables re: Quezon's statement about coming to U.S. in New York Times, which upset Sumulong</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon (Monrovia). 5 page letter (Nov. 10, 1930) re: his legislative work in Philippines</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. 5 page letter (Jan. 6, 1931) re: events in U.S. and Sumulong's T. R.</item><item>Quezon to Parker. 3 page letter (Jan. 11, 1931) re: Secretary of War's appointments in Philippines</item><item>J. Laurel to Quezon. Letter (March 20, 1931) re: mostly Tayabas election problems, esp. Laurel vs. Recto, re: also Recto's negative campaign and trickiness, Laurel exhibits much animosity toward Recto, and expresses much loyalty to Quezon</item><item>Rector to Quezon. Letter (March 24, 1931) re: his struggle with Laurel, suggests a link with Quezon but unclear</item><item>Quezon to Laurel. Letter (April 16, 1931) Quezon expresses his support for Laurel and tells him to use this letter but it is not a super positive letter of support as Quezon can write</item><item>Considerable correspondence re: "Ang Bagong Katipunan"--begun allegedly by Roxas and Cumena--mostly negative and some fearful of its outcome--some hint that Governor-General quieted down Roxas' activities in this regard</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_5b729843e25b74dda77af8e9fc485f9c" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1931-07-25/1932-06-29" type="inclusive">July 25, 1931-June 29, 1932</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">15</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 15, July 25, 1931-June 29, 1932, with notes and comments of Michael Cullinane</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>P. J. Hurley (Secretary of War)</item><item>F. McIntyre, J. Harbord--continuing correspondence</item><item>J. Switzer</item><item>William Montavan (Director, Legal Department, National Catholic Welfare Conference)</item><item>Senator H. Hawes, esp. 7 page letter, Aguinaldo to H. Hawes (July 25, 1931) re: independence issue</item><item>C. Osias and P. Guevara (Resid. Comms.--heavy official correspondence re: independence or autonomy issue, Osias often expresses his loyalty to Quezon</item><item>Osrox (Osmeña and Roxas) mission to U.S., heavy correspondence with Quaqual (Quezon, Aquino, Alas) re: work for independence bill, i.e. HHC Bill, much of it confidential</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>Vicente Madrigal and Amande Avanlena (Nec. Ollid, President, Confed. de Assoces y Plantaduces de Cana-dulce)</item><item>Rafael Palma</item><item>A. Hurrillenu (Judge, Zamboanga) re: independence issue</item><item>Faustino Aguilar (Secretary of Senate) re: situation in Philippines (Manila) to Quezon (Aug. 11, 1931)</item><item>Walter Robb (American Chamber of Commerce)</item><item>George C. Butte (Alternative Governor-General) esp. 6 page letter (many drafts) from Quezon (Jan. 7, 1932) re: sugar planters and how they should get a bigger piece of the pie, more for small guy</item><item>Maximo Kalaw, esp. M. Kalaw to Quezon. Letter (Oct. 5, 1931) re: new Filipino mood toward independence</item><item>Ramon Fernandez, esp. Quezon to R. Fernandez. 5 page letter (Spanish), Jan 25, 1932, re: a concerned group of citizens who wired directly to Bureau of Internal Affairs stressing desire for immediate independence, Quezon reprimands them slightly for not going thru the mission (greeting to "Mi querido compadre")</item><item>Philippine Sugar Association, esp: 7 page letter to T. Roosevelt, Jr. (March 11, 1932) with charts and tables, etc., copy of letter to Quezon [much correspondence on sugar industry]</item><item>Antonio de las Alas (Acting Speaker) esp.: a 4 page letter from Quezon (May 25, 1932) re: independence issue and Philippine legislators' contacts with the mission</item><item>Juan Sumulong, esp. Quezon to Sumulong. 4 page letter (Feb. 10, 1932) re: Sumulong's opposition to the publicity fund for the Mission to the U.S.</item><item>Also letter from Quezon to Senator [?] (of Pasay, Rizil) long 7 page letter in Tagalog (Jan. 8, 1932) re: politics in Manila and Philippines, Democratas, Osmeña, Mission to U.S., etc. [possibly to Sumulong]</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_8515acb7ea4526c591d2ce50c3555e13" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1932-06-29/1933-08-10" type="inclusive">June 29, 1932-August 10, 1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">16</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 16, June 29, 1932-August 10, 1933, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Heavy correspondence with "Osrox" (Washington) re: stateside legislation, etc.</item><item>F. McIntyre (Philippine Trade Commission)</item><item>C. Osias</item><item>Amando Avancena (Cadiz, Negros Occidental) and other sugar related correspondence and memorandums in Quezon's possession</item><item>H. L. Stimson</item><item>J. Switzer</item><item>Many U. S. Congressmen (esp. Senators Hawes and Hare)</item><item>Roy Howard (New York)--a close friend who refers to Quezon as "My dear Casey"</item><item>F. B. Harrison</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>J. L. Headington (V. Pres., Philippine Button Company) re: Philippine business</item><item>E. D. Hester (advisor to Governor-General)</item><item>C. P. Romulo</item><item>E. Quirino</item><item>F. Buencamino</item><item>Rafael Palma</item><item>J. Bocobo</item><item>R. Fernandez</item><item>Quintin Paredes (Speaker pro tem, House)</item><item>S. Osmeña (slight during this period, i.e. personal correspondence)</item><item>Resolution by a Committee of American Democrats in Philippines</item><item>Federico Mangahas (The Tribune) re: a letter by Quezon (not sent) in response to a "vicious" attack by Mangahas in press (Dec., 1932)</item></list></item><item>Significant correspondence: <list type="simple"><item>Aguinaldo to Osmeña (Washington). Letter (Aug. 12, 1932) re: his desire to know the truth about what's going on in Washington, he repeats all the anti-Mission information in Manila press</item><item>Osmeña to Aguinaldo. 22 page letter (September 30, 1932) a complete reply, answering each of the above accusations, explaining in detail the Mission's work and their position on H-H-C Bill</item><item>Osias to Osmeña 5 page letter (Aug. 22, 1932) re: a denial by Osias that he has attacked the independence mission</item><item>E. D. Hester to Quezon. Letter (Aug. 27, 1932) re: Philippine tariff</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Letter (Oct. 3, 1932) re: his letter and correspondence with Aguinaldo</item><item>Quezon to Romulo. 4 page letter (not sent), Nov. 1, 1932, re: Senate maneuvering and his alleged favoring of opposition Sen. (i.e. Relto) over his governorship</item><item>Quezon to Senator Teofilo Sison. 3 page letter and enclosure (Nov. 11, 1932) re: a tribute to General Luna</item><item>Quezon to Senator B. Aquino. Letter (Spanish), Nov. 14, 1932 re: his work in the U.S.</item><item>Quezon to MacArthur. Cable (n.d. but after Dec. 30, 1932) re: MacArthur's stand on Philippine independence</item><item>M. Kalaw to Quezon. 2 page letter (Spanish), Jan. 4, 1933, re: his desire to be ideologically reunited with Quezon, but with certain guarantees first, in Nationalista stand on independence</item><item>Quezon to M. Kalaw. 13 pages of drafts Jan 8, 1933, mailed Jan. 9, 1933. re: his reply with much explanation of his activities in Washington during debates over Jones Bill and Clarke Amendment, mainly re: Quezon's split with the Mission leaders</item><item>Luis R. de Luzuriaga (writing from Cebu) to Quezon. Letter (Feb. 19, 1933) re: sugar question and business proposal to Quezon, he is currently working for Socony-Vacuum Corporation in Cebu, was a former associate of Rafael Alunan</item><item>M. Kalaw to Quezon. Letter (May 29, 1933) re: common action by both legislative mission and independence mission (in Washington) over independence bills</item><item>Quezon to Harrison. Cable (July 2, 1933) re: obtaining Harrison's support of the "anti" view and Osmeña's prior fears with Clarke amendment</item><item>Harrison to Quezon Cable (July 5, 1933) --Harrison's favorable reply</item><item>Ramon Torres (Bago, Negros Occidental) to Quezon. 3 page letter in Spanish (July 4, 1933)--he is an "anti" and will support Quezon but wants to maintain party unity if possible, some about Negros Occidental politics</item><item>Quezon to R. Torres. 4 page letter in Spanish (after 5 drafts) (July 8, 1933)--Quezon's reply, explaining his opposition to H-H-C Bill, and the difficulties with Osmeña over H-H-C and why split is necessary</item><item>Some correspondence over financial matter is found between Murphy and V. Singson Encarnacion (Acting Secretary of Finance)</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_2900ccac2169bf6bf78d23cfb7329b42" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1933-08-11/1934-06-07" type="inclusive">August 11, 1933-June 7, 1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">17</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 17, August 11, 1933-June 7, 1934, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Many U. S. Congressmen, esp. Senator McDuffie, Representative Sabath (Iowa), Senator King and Senator P. Harrison</item><item>Some copies of Secretary of War to Governor-General</item><item>Sugar Philippines--lobby of Philippine Sugar interests in Washington, esp.: Rafael Alunan--much on sugar in 1934</item><item>Creed F. Cox (Chief, Bureau Insular Affairs)</item><item>William Baldwin (New York)</item><item>F. D. R. on occasion</item><item>I. Garaldon (while both were in Washington)</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>J. Bocobo (memos re: H-H-C Bill, "Plebicite", etc.)</item><item>V. Singson Encarnacion to Murphy re: financial matters</item><item>Quirico Abeto (Secretary of Justice) in Spanish</item><item>T. Kalaw (National Library)</item><item>E. Aguinaldo (mostly re: his going to U.S. with independence mission of legislation)</item><item>Frank Murphy</item></list></item><item>Significant correspondence: <list type="simple"><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Letter (not sent) (Oct. 15, 1933) re: minority caucus in Senate headed by Osmeña and also re: H-H-C Bill</item><item>Quezon to Osmeña. Letter (Oct. 19, 1933) re: some questions sent by Osmeña</item><item>Tirona (Rep., Cavite). 3 page letter (Spanish) (Oct. 31, 1933) A very sharp criticism of Quezon, mainly due to his stateside activities as nominal head independence mission: "...en ver de asistir a las sesiones de Copgreso, y trabajar cerca del mismo por nuestra indep., se fue usted directamente a Monrovia, para to mar vacaciones a costa de Juan de la cruz..." Tirona stresses that he is unafraid of Quezon or anyone!</item><item>V. Singson Encarnacion to J. Vargas. Letter (Dec. 11, 1933) and (Dec. 21, 1933) re: mostly sugar and other Philippine crops and resources</item><item>Recto to Governor-General. 5 page letter (Jan. 7, 1934) re: constitutional problems</item><item>Memorandum on Philippine-American trade relations by Quezon (Jan., 1934) 17 pages</item><item>American Philippine policy 13 pages (Jan., 1934) 13 drafts (one to be signed Quezon, Quirino, Gabaldon, Guevara</item><item>C. E. Russell to Quezon. Letter (Jan. 16, 1934) re: the failing of Quezon's memorandum (above) and how it will not get the desired results</item><item>Recto-Paredes to Quezon. Letter (Feb. 3, 1934) re: a resolution on Philippine independence passed by a mass meeting in Manila the day before</item><item>G. T. Peabody (Mindanao-Pacific Corp., Ltd.) to Quezon. Letter (Feb. 15, 1934) re: economic situation</item><item>Quezon to I. Gabaldon. Letter (March 24, 1934) re: Quezon's explanation to I.G. about Quezon's actions concerning the H-H-C Bill and subsequent</item><item>Cabrera to Quezon. Telegram (April 4, 1934) re: defeating Roxas</item><item>Roxas to Quezon. 2 page letter (May 10, 1934) a somewhat angry letter reacting to Quezon's quote in papers about him, Roxas explains he is a "technical man" not desiring to bother with politics, wants to go back to the farm, says he's not a "pro" or any other political classification--he then praises Quezon</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_8f78db79ceb484295d19aeb73d18c6a9" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1934-06-07/1935-11-14" type="inclusive">June 7, 1934-November 14, 1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">18</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 18 (part), June 7, 1934-November 14, 1935, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Frequent memorandums re: economic problems: tariffs, trade, sugar, other crops, and products, esp. by V. Singson Encarnacion, and R. Alunan (P. Sugar Assoc.)</item><item>Secretary of War</item><item>Creed Cox</item><item>Senator Howes, McDuffie, etc.</item><item>William Baldwin (New York)</item><item>Neuss, Hesslein, and Company, Inc. (New York)</item><item>Cordace Institution (J.S. McDaniel)</item><item>Hanson, Orth and Stevenson, Inc. (London)</item><item>Roy Howard (Scripts-Howard Newspapers--New York)--heavy in late 1935, early 1936</item><item>Leonidas Dyer (Lawyer, St. Louis, Missouri)</item><item>MacArthur, Douglas</item><item>F. A. Delgado (President, Comm. from Philippines--late 1935)</item><item>Morgan Shuster (New York)</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>"Don Miguel"</item><item>C. M. Recto</item><item>T. M. Kalaw</item><item>P. Guevara re: his running for office with or without Quezon's support depending on his stand</item><item>Vicente Lim re: Philippine national defense, some on Americanization of Filipinos and its negative results</item><item>Frank Murphy</item></list></item><item>Significant correspondence: <list type="simple"><item>Senator Hawes to Roxas. Letter (Nov. 7, 1934) re: Hawes' praise of Roxas</item><item>Dr. [?] to Quezon. Letter (n.d.) very interesting response to a Quezon letter re: nationalist movements in Indonesia and some about Javanese nobility</item><item>J. Yulo to Quezon. Letter (Jan. 7, 1935) re: Quezon's appointment of him to Supreme Court, a personal explanation of why he is opposed</item><item>Quezon to Murphy. Letter (Jan. 8, 1935) re: (among others) the Sakdalistas in Tayabas and Laguna</item><item>Quezon to Malcolm. Letter (Jan. 21, 1935)--a critique of Malcolm's manuscript (book) about Quezon's political machine and other issues</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Telegram (March 18, 1935) re: coalition prospects</item><item>Vargas to Quezon. Radiogram (April 1, 1935) re: Sumulong's stand on coalition and some on activities of the - Sakdalistas</item><item>Vargas to Quezon. Radiogram (April 21, 1935) re: Sumulong's stand on coalition and some on activities of the - Sakdalistas</item><item>Vargas to Quezon. Radiogram (April 24, 1935) re: Sumulong's stand on coalition and some on activities of the - Sakdalistas</item><item>Quezon to Vargas. Radiogram (April 24, 1935 re: Sumulong's stand on coalition and some on activities of the - Sakdalistas</item><item>Vargas to Quezon. Radiogram (April 29, 1935) re: Sumulong's article "Highlights given" --article: "After Coalition the Decline" in Manila papers April 27th.</item><item>Vargas to Quezon. Radiogram (May 3, 1935) re: Sumulong's article, Quezon's stand</item><item>Confederate n.d. reports to Quezon re: Sakdalista uprising early May, 1935</item><item>C. Rumulo to Quezon. 8 page letter (May 15, 1935) re: political situation. Report to Quezon including Sakdalista revolt, newspapers stands on day's issues --writing as the publisher of D-M-H-M Newspapers (Debate, Mabuhay, Herald, Monday mail)</item><item>Recto Roxas Alunan to Quezon. Radiogram (May 21, 1935)</item><item>Yulo to Quezon. Letter (May 27, 1935) re: national assembly for coalition and pres. campaign, enclosed a brief statement re: ones against Sakdals in various towns</item><item>Quezon to Sumulong. Telegram (Aug. 30, 1935) re: Sumulong's attack on him.</item><item>Laurel to Quezon. Letter (Sept. 2, 1935) re: Sumulong's article, he wants Quezon to deny the quote ascribed to Quezon in Bulletin (which he cites and which serves as the main thrust in Sumulong's argument)</item><item>Quezon to Laurel. Letter (Sept. 5, 1935): he denies above statement, says he never made it at all</item><item>Quezon to Paredes. Letter (Oct. 24, 1935): offers him a post as Resid. Comm.</item><item>Paredes to Quezon. Letter 14 pages (Nov. 3, 1935)--expresses his continued opposition to complete coalition (or fusion); also explains that he can do more as speaker of National Assembly; he explains its functions and possibilities</item><item>Quezon to Paredes. 19 page letter (Nov. 6, 1935)--presents his side and views regarding the National Assembly</item><item>Aguinaldo to Secretary of War. 3 page letter (Nov. 3, 1935) re: his particular distaste for recent election conduct, especially for Commonwealth President, where he lost, claims widespread fraud occurred, P.C. harassment, etc.</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_9bcad650cb239691fed4aa3b322e724b" level="subseries"><did><unittitle>President of the Commonwealth of the Philippines</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>The President of the Commonwealth of the Philippines (1935-1944; Reels 18-21) subseries covers Quezon's tenure as president, the passage of social legislation, and the war with Japan. For the years 1936 to 1944, there is substantially reduced documentation compared to the previous two subseries and almost no correspondence for 1938.</p></scopecontent><c03 id="aspace_6ff4731502d0e11a35556777847db916" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1935-11-15/1937-02-26" type="inclusive">November 15, 1935-February 26, 1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">18</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 18 (part), November 15, 1935-February 26, 1937, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane</p><list type="ordered"><item>Quezon to Jose E. Romero (Floor Leader). 10 page letter (March 15, 1936) re: rights of National Assembly members</item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_c4ca3e0237705687ab5e3c6185c9631b" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1937-03-11/1939-10-18" type="inclusive">March 11, 1937-October 18, 1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">19</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 19, March 11, 1937-October 18, 1939, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>L. G. Dyer (Lawyer, St. Louis) re: Philippine cause, aiding Quezon</item><item>J. O. Adler (New York Times) and S. Fisher, Jr. (New York Times)</item><item>Paul V. McNutt</item><item>General C. Burnett (Chief, R.I.A.)--1939</item><item>Frank Murphy, Roy Howard--continuing personal correspondence, esp: Quezon to Murphy, July 8, 1937 where Quezon thanks for Murphy for his recent hospitality in Detroit</item><item>Harry H. Woodring (Secretary of War--late 1937)</item><item>Francis Sayre</item><item>Franklin Delano Roosevelt--on occasion</item><item>Many U.S. Congressmen, e.g. Senator Hawes, Tydings, P. Harrison and Sabath, King and Representative Kocialkowski re: Joint Preparation Committee on Philippine Affairs</item><item>Much correspondence with Joint Preparation Committee on Philippine Affairs with Osmeña, the head of Philippine delegation; many letters re: Joint Preparation Committee on Philippine Affairs work in letters of Osmeña to Quezon, especially Jan. 1939, much of which concern sugar; these letters include enclosures of Osmeña's correspondence with others in Washington, especially Senator Hawes and W. C. Forbes [helping Osmeña]</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. Radiogram (July 10, 1939) re: Quezon's efforts to change constitution so he can run for a second term of office as Commonwealth. President; Osmeña favorable to idea</item><item>J. M. Elizalde (London and Resid. Comm.) "Mike"--regular and official correspondence</item><item>F. Buencamino, Jr. (London)--business mostly</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>J. Vargas, esp.: <list type="simple"><item>Vargas to Quezon. Cable (April 3, 1937) re: legislation endorsements of Quezon's activities in Washington</item><item>Quezon to Vargas. 4 page letter (April 8, 1937) (en route Mexico) re: his progress in U.S.</item></list> </item><item>Q. Paredes</item><item>[Roxas, Romero, Razon]</item><item>Jose Yulo ("My Dear Joe")</item><item>Charles Romulo: long 7 page letter (many drafts), Oct. 30, 1937, re: history and contribution of Philippine Herald on its anniversary</item><item>Locsin (Negros Occidental) include 8 page letter to Quezon (Aug. 3, 1937) re: many items, esp. trade, tariffs on agricultural goods, etc. and U.S. Congressional action</item><item>Speaker [Montilla (Negros Occidental)]? esp. 6 page letter from Quezon, Aug. 30, 1937, re: Quezon's views on Philippine party coalition and fusion (1st draft); also Quezon to Speaker, long 3 page letter n.d. re: coalition and fusion</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_9af7e7adce7e65bd62f23f2ebd0d4000" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1939-10-18/1942-11-30" type="inclusive">October 18, 1939-November 30, 1942</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">20</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 20, October 18, 1939-November 30, 1942, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>J. M. Elizalde (Resid. Comm.)--very heavy official correspondence</item><item>Frank Murphy, especially to "Justice" Murphy, a petition from the Philippine Assembly (Jan. 29, 1940) re: getting clemency for F. Buencamino, Jr.</item><item>Sergio Osmeña (while in U.S.)</item><item>LaGuardia (New York) re: Philippine entry in New York World's Fair--eventually no funds to set up facilities</item><item>G. Fairchild</item><item>F. D. Roosevelt, much in Dec. 1942 to Jan. 1942 re: Philippine loyalty, requesting funds, international priorities, etc.</item><item>Secretary Harold Ickes (Interior), C. Holl, Abe Fortas, Henry Stimson (Much after Pearl Harbor)</item><item>Manuel Avila Camacho (Pres. Mexico): Quezon congratulations for winning Presidency of Mexico</item><item>W. P. Simms (Solipp--Howard Newspapers) Quezon attacks them for their attacks on him, blames U.S. for 55 year of misrule (Dec. 4, 1941)</item></list></item><item>Communications with individuals in Manila and the Philippines: <list type="simple"><item>F. Sayre</item><item>MacArthur, slight until Pearl Harbor, then quite heavy; Memorandum of military adviser (Dec. 9, 1939) 20 pages</item><item>Claude Buss (Executive Assistant to High Commissioner)</item><item>Sergio Osmeña, esp.: <list type="simple"><item>Osmeña to Quezon. 2 page memo (confidential), Dec. 27, 1939, re: Osmeña's dislike of Elizalde's actions of belittling work of mission in Washington, Osmeña says Elizalde (after his return) overstressed his contribution to the cause, Osmeña defends the mission [notes also that he is unable to get an appointment with Quezon]</item><item>Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page confidential letter (Dec. 31, 1939) asks if Mission can be given opportunity to answer each of Elizalde's charges</item></list> </item><item>Yulo, esp. (in Washington and Manila) <list type="simple"><item>Quezon and Vargas to Yulo. Radiogram (Oct. 25, 1940) re: the selection of Ramon Torres as compromise candidate for Governor of Negros</item><item>Quezon to Yulo. 2 page letter (Feb. 24, 1941) re: an explanation of political points which Yulo was disturbed over, also re: the near "Fight in Negros" between inter-party factions, also re: the Yulo--Alunan dispute</item></list> </item><item>R. Alunan, esp. (Secretary of Interior) Quezon to R. Alunan. Letter (May 6, 1941) re: the necessity of Philippine loyalty to U.S. at this time of stress, especially in response to Socialist Communist anti-imperialist dogma--should outlaw their meetings (wants Alunan to do this within municipalities and provinces</item><item>Leon Guinto, esp. 5 page memo to Quezon (May 23, 1941) "A Plan to Check Communism in Philippines"</item><item>Ricardo D. Miranda (Acting Governor, Province of Davao) esp. a letter (Feb. 6, 1942) to Teofisto Guingona (Commissioner for Mindanao and Sulu) 5 pages plus letter and enclosures--i.e. events in area to do with Japanese attack during December, 1941.</item><item>Mayor Delgado (Cebu), especially <list type="simple"><item>Delgado to Quezon, Cable (Feb. 7, 1941) re: the Visayas--"Civilian morale good"</item><item>Other correspondence on Visayas exists for this period, talk of bolstering up the area (especially Cebu, Negros, Panay)</item><item>5 page memo (May 5, 1941) by Quezon to National Assembly re: national security in the event of war</item></list> </item><item>Quezon to "People of America" (Dec. 20, 1941) re: Philippine plight, plea for support</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03><c03 id="aspace_14189c5516588bac293a0d6ac5f1e8de" level="file"><did><unitdate normal="1942-12-03/1944-08" type="inclusive">December 3, 1942-August 1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">21</container></did><scopecontent><p>Highlights of roll 21, December 3, 1942-August 1944, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane</p><list type="ordered"><item>Communications (almost entirely) with individuals in the United States: <list type="simple"><item>Franklin Delano Roosevelt</item><item>Abe Fortas (Acting Secretary of Interior)</item><item>Henry Stimson</item><item>MacArthur (much from Australia)</item><item>Cordell Hull</item><item>Walter Lippman (Washington Post)</item><item>F. S. Marquardt (Chicago Sun)</item><item>Sergio Osmeña--heavy, some still in Spanish</item><item>Tomas Confesor (in Philippines), June to November, 1943, with correspondence with Quezon re: Panay during war</item><item>J. M. Elizalde</item><item>Frank Murphy</item><item>Sumner Welles</item><item>F. B. Harrison</item><item>Harold Ickes (Secretary of Interior)</item><item>Many U.S. Congressmen, especially Representative Bell, Senator Tydings</item><item>Col. Carlos P. Romulo (Information Secretary, Resid. Comm.)</item><item>J. C. Dionigio</item><item>Lt. Col. A. Suriano (Secretary of Finance)</item><item>Eugenio S. Del Rosacio (Re. of Misamis Occidental), esp. 2 page letter (May 14-25, 1943) re: situation in Misamis</item><item>Carlos P. Garcia (Senator, Bohol), esp. 2 page letter to Quezon from "somewhere in Bohol" re: situation in that Province and the Visayas</item><item>Mrs. Pilar Lim (wife Vicente Lim who is in Philippines) re: his loyalty and her sustenance check</item><item>Conrado D. Marapao (Province Governor, Bohol) esp., 2 page letter to Roosevelt (July 17, 1943) re: situation and war in Visayas and Bohol and the funding of anti-Japanese activities</item><item>L. Jesus Cuenco and Miguel Cuenco. Letter (Nov. 6, 1943) to Quezon from Leyte re: some event in Philippines; also 3 page letter Quezon to M. Jesus Cuenco (Jan. 28, 1944)</item></list></item></list></scopecontent></c03></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_57ed8f45d445b27bf9530ea5eb8eb401" level="series"><did><unittitle>Speeches, Articles, Statements, Reports, Interviews, and Book File</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>Speech, Article, Statement, Report, Interview, and Book File (1907-1944; Reels 22-46). This series includes handwritten, typewritten, near-print and printed copies of drafts of speeches (some in various stages), articles, remarks, press releases, and press conferences; also manuscript and background materials assembled by Quezon in the writing of his autobiography <title render="italic">The Good Fight</title> (if any). The series is arranged by type of material and then chronologically.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_4df134f85303b591d55b1ec5369e5ed8" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1909/1913" type="inclusive">1909-1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">22</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_e86c40a13276b5f81dec06ad6178ce93" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914-04-15/1917" type="inclusive">April 15, 1914-1917 undated</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">23</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_e2688edd207603bc71c4579e983a5bd2" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1918/1920-08-02" type="inclusive">1918-August 2, 1920</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">24</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_c0f7ed066b0cecfce23862b00e75ca0c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920-04-20/1921" type="inclusive">August 20, 1920-1921 undated</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">25</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_03bf87584ed99addb28bfc40df47fe0e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1921/1923-11-13" type="inclusive">1921 undated-November 13, 1923</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">26</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_8a177da80bbd1f26c9521a8b3ae0461e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1923-12-07/1925-09-28" type="inclusive">December 7, 1923-September 28, 1925</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">27</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_d51580578e5feb67e1f0d376a4eff739" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925-10-14/1926" type="inclusive">October 14, 1925-1926 undated</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">28</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_5313e9a7c6af20eca26392dfa91e40bb" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1926/1927" type="inclusive">1926 undated-1927 undated</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">29</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_e9b6ef78fffb91ce4c748d3ceee51410" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches 1927 undated Articles 1928</unittitle><unitdate normal="1927/1928" type="inclusive">1927-1928</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">30</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ec31c0c20f67be91d1965af1f3812527" level="file"><did><unittitle>Miscellaneous writings 1928 Speeches, 1931 (Quezon Report)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1928/1931" type="inclusive">1928-1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">31</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_a0bb7d0a551e75c86f0f2f2c14d70065" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1931-10-27/1932-10-19" type="inclusive">October 27, 1931-October 19, 1932</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">32</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_34fc55517df4734c21185298b7e3d416" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1932-10-26/1933-07-28" type="inclusive">October 26, 1932-July 28, 1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">33</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_8bedfaaf66d5007241821c382bbb38d0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1933-07-28/1933-07-28" type="inclusive">July 28, 1933</unitdate><unitdate certainty="approximate" normal="1933/1933" type="inclusive">1933 undated</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">34</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_7cf514169a9f0ba3e55a11aef51f5cb7" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches 1933 undated Articles, 1933 (Kalaw)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1933/1933" type="inclusive">1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">35</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_28e5dfb7de8751b66cb3ed1fe2809e68" level="file"><did><unittitle>Articles 1933 (Kalaw)-Articles, 1934</unittitle><unitdate normal="1933/1934" type="inclusive">1933-1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">36</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_446d37237b68ecfe1a1a28f047804da6" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1935/1935-11-25" type="inclusive">1935-November 25, 1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">37</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_794abdea93de2502c4ae07f65b5715b0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches, November 25, 1935-Press releases</unittitle><unitdate normal="1936-09-04/1936-09-04" type="inclusive">September 4, 1936</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">38</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_92c8e4187f15aca50500a4767132a5c2" level="file"><did><unittitle>Press releases September 4, 1936 Speeches, December 25, 1937</unittitle><unitdate normal="1936/1937" type="inclusive">1936-1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">39</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_02992ac16a45d9de8412a879e0fec07e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches December 30, 1937 Miscellaneous writings, 1937</unittitle><unitdate normal="1937/1937" type="inclusive">1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">40</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_25fc21f704d7ec8cc0259a79efca0153" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches January 15, 1938 Articles, 1938</unittitle><unitdate normal="1938/1938" type="inclusive">1938</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">41</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_debb9cc34c3e9b58df5f629221915d30" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1939-01-06/1939-08-19" type="inclusive">January 6, 1939-August 19, 1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">42</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_a7b1b0f5b2a5b8e4d0bf6aa6ccc28be6" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1939-08-20/1940-01-22" type="inclusive">August 20, 1939-January 22, 1940</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">43</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_c41e373322db045bf0cfea4dd9d86bc3" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1940-05-18/1941-06-19" type="inclusive">May 18, 1940-June 19, 1941</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">44</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_9063ee3a2369dcad65a864581c6a5984" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches</unittitle><unitdate normal="1941-06-19/1943-05-30" type="inclusive">June 19, 1941-May 30, 1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">45</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_a5ef10c71c3b95d5e3d2a6aa6c8b9790" level="file"><did><unittitle>Speeches Speech, Article, Statement, Report, Interview File</unittitle><unitdate normal="1943-07-14/1943-07-14" type="inclusive">July 14, 1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">46</container></did></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_7ff52e15b00ecfe7209687f016c8c05c" level="series"><did><unittitle>Correspondents File</unittitle></did><scopecontent><p>Correspondents File (1910-1944; Reels 47-54). This series consists of letters, telegrams, cablegrams, radiograms and memoranda sent and received. It is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and then chronologically. The letters in this series are in English unless otherwise indicated.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_9f7448e3a9afdbc3d6b86825765d385f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Marcario Adriatico</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1916" type="inclusive">1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_0b0190551db814d93d4e615974f6610e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Felipe Agoncillo</unittitle><unitdate normal="1922/1922" type="inclusive">1922</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_fcb3aa47b3708794d5b31b6be9ba2ebb" level="file"><did><unittitle>Emilio Agoncillo</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1935" type="inclusive">1913-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish, Tagalog, English)</p></odd><odd><p>(much that was not in "General Correspondence",--some clippings re: Aguinaldo's campaign against Quezon (1935))</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_3d782cdc59f508f0644a839ceeb67dbb" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jose Alejandrino (Senator and later General)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1918/1935" type="inclusive">1918-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish with some English)</p></odd><odd><p>(mostly re: his 1924-25 litigation against Quezon)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_b3e2253a512a056555171b2310422e2b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Rafael Alunan</unittitle><unitdate normal="1910/1937" type="inclusive">1910-1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><odd><p>(includes much of his personal correspondence not found in "General Correspondence")</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_b8c40bbdf620688fa70c7de146b03f55" level="file"><did><unittitle>Rosa S. de Arvero (Directora, Instituta de Mujeres)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1930" type="inclusive">1920-1930</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_e40ca69509fc8c150932d314b2884b2e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Timothy Ansberry (Lawyer, New York)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1929" type="inclusive">1916-1929</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_25145bdea9b18ba955c3c9f1e9da3cf5" level="file"><did><unittitle>Benigno Aquino (Senator)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1935" type="inclusive">1920-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_cccf882be8ad1ffbe07d16528d3c1bbc" level="file"><did><unittitle>Sotero Buluyot</unittitle><unitdate normal="1918/1937" type="inclusive">1918-1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_e73d40973ca881c6206579a2932dd358" level="file"><did><unittitle>H. H. Bandholtz</unittitle><unitdate normal="1909/1923" type="inclusive">1909-1923</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(includes some correspondence not found in "General Correspondence")</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_140f3be10f64bcc4bd4004ae315f07b2" level="file"><did><unittitle>James Blount</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1915" type="inclusive">1912-1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(mostly re: his book and his state of poverty after its completion)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_6af8e53c78ce1d60a666212a6e3ff24e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jorge Bocobo</unittitle><unitdate normal="1923/1931" type="inclusive">1923-1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_3f2dc62c077abe80574ea3e5875c2336" level="file"><did><unittitle>Representative William Bor</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1916" type="inclusive">1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_a83c65e5ad075fce2eeace262e577982" level="file"><did><unittitle>Clement L. Bouve (Lawyer, Washington, D.C.)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1927" type="inclusive">1911-1927</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ae699a15552a68e2a2aece61fce7554a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Felipe Buencamino, Jr.</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1930" type="inclusive">1914-1930</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_df495fbdeb1a8da5787f0a91144e4c16" level="file"><did><unittitle>Frank Carpenter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1908/1929" type="inclusive">1908-1929</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(some re: Mindanao, Sulu)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_e20604744458267696785ac94324ca43" level="file"><did><unittitle>Representative H. M. Chalmers</unittitle><unitdate normal="1927/1927" type="inclusive">1927</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_d5de46b821c7c13ee3536e85e154346e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jose A. Clarin (Senator, Bohol)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1935" type="inclusive">1917-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(mostly Spanish)</p></odd><odd><p>(much more than in General Correspondence--some re: changing name of Tulun to Sikatuna and his election and striving to be Senator protempore-1929 he died 1935)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_665fcdad781694b9b97c2252078d994d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Clark Bennett</unittitle><unitdate normal="1933/1933" type="inclusive">1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_b151022ac40eb7eb7aef3938007d897f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Tomas Confesor</unittitle><unitdate normal="1927/1943" type="inclusive">1927-1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ea08823d38b0ad26b4410add0e6b5389" level="file"><did><unittitle>Austin Craig</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1927" type="inclusive">1916-1927</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">47</container></did><odd><p>(mostly English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_5252da0afebece97f3cfabbc10403050" level="file"><did><unittitle>Austin Craig (cont.)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1927/1937" type="inclusive">1927-1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(much personal, interest; also much to do with his "Rizal's Own Story")</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_0a6c47bc1c6640133fb5c9438bf2724c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Dwight Davis</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1931" type="inclusive">1929-1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_91b28de8361652e224d42dd276f273df" level="file"><did><unittitle>Francis Dexter (Lawyer, Puerto Rico)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1917" type="inclusive">1917</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_1e3de7d0a32c1711a7460f936131dec6" level="file"><did><unittitle>Ramon Diokno</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1940" type="inclusive">1920-1940</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish)</p></odd><odd><p>(mostly re: transcript of a litigation)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_8aeee84e08265ed9e2760a51f87b05ab" level="file"><did><unittitle>Harold Dollar (Dollar Steamship Liner)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925/1934" type="inclusive">1925-1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_b427f2b7eef77527b16440f2f67cd628" level="file"><did><unittitle>Manuel Earnshaw (brother of Tomas)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1933" type="inclusive">1920-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_91ffbf5dc0009b33f73d76f76228a61d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Tomas Earnshaw</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1932" type="inclusive">1917-1932</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_6fb7de0e9f6c9381a2d84c00d6847978" level="file"><did><unittitle>Alfred Ehrman</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1941" type="inclusive">1920-1941</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(mostly re: S. F. business)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_70eb19b7f124558fe24a3b659dc87af1" level="file"><did><unittitle>Joaquin Miguel Elizalde</unittitle><unitdate normal="1935/1944" type="inclusive">1935-1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_6e1e092da2cb34b6b1f15aea0db8d982" level="file"><did><unittitle>Joseph Evens (Col.)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1943/1944" type="inclusive">1943-1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(one letter, August 26, 1943 re: resistance on Bohol, Senator Garcia)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_64ca6e85dc9f70dc5a735f7707cbbba1" level="file"><did><unittitle>George Fairchild (Senator)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1941" type="inclusive">1916-1941</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_a36efd02b03881815b0e68bde3109a5c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Harriott E. Fansler (New York)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1912" type="inclusive">1912</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_c43402c5a5f5dd2495587206366ad3f1" level="file"><did><unittitle>James A. Farley letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1944/1944" type="inclusive">1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_0afdca637f3e9d441f75cc5a757936ba" level="file"><did><unittitle>Ramon Fernandez</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1934" type="inclusive">1917-1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><odd><p>(mostly on business)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_6e2357d3ce3d8ff2bbf5a559b9833045" level="file"><did><unittitle>A. P. Fitzsimmons (M.D., Nebraska)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1931/1932" type="inclusive">1931-1932</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_070b6afc127aa37eb0112368677df01b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Abe Fortas letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1942/1942" type="inclusive">1942</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_b9f9d90660e7080d888eaa2769609130" level="file"><did><unittitle>James Frear (Washington, D.C.)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1939" type="inclusive">1920-1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_9ae3a878dc0e7163bb20c60445e8df46" level="file"><did><unittitle>Isauro Gabaldon</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1923" type="inclusive">1917-1923</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><odd><p>(heavy official correspondence in cables, etc. while in Washington)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_f338486058e256d1625f8865aacf04ec" level="file"><did><unittitle>Patrick Gallagher</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1916" type="inclusive">1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_9beb4f57b3ab005aef4d2e72f5821484" level="file"><did><unittitle>Eugene A. Gilmore</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1929" type="inclusive">1929</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(official correspondence)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_1ee3e478b6eb8600f06b843e5e75def8" level="file"><did><unittitle>Fernando M. Guerrero (former secretary of the Philippine Senate)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1927" type="inclusive">1916-1927</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_a37dc865bb6b9841ab82379e9135e70e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Pedro Guevara</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1932" type="inclusive">1915-1932</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><odd><p>(mostly official correspondence)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_2191ec7ba9d38d0642d6a04bf85c2066" level="file"><did><unittitle>Teopisto Guingona (Bureau of Non-Christian Tribes--later Judge 1st Instance)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1932" type="inclusive">1920-1932</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_8d5dafc01a1375829aeb63ae540b8d5c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Leon G. Guinto (later Provincial governor Laguna)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1918/1937" type="inclusive">1918-1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_b4b96f3c06a7c33e915af7d372e97114" level="file"><did><unittitle>W. H. Lawrence (Banker) letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1919/1919" type="inclusive">1919</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_b6ce0a94379fda7b11e93e77cfc8a2ea" level="file"><did><unittitle>Benito Legarda</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1912" type="inclusive">1911-1912</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">48</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_cf287d03f1f503902ea3c5931d81042a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Benito Legarda (cont.)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1912" type="inclusive">1911-1912</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_8d03d8f321329c81306626515a121101" level="file"><did><unittitle>James Harbord</unittitle><unitdate normal="1910/1933" type="inclusive">1910-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did><odd><p>(personal correspondence)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_f451ddca8e6493bdce2e2129d8e3eb97" level="file"><did><unittitle>F. B. Harrison</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1935" type="inclusive">1917-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_cc0a728f588d440cd37f7e2d18cc4447" level="file"><did><unittitle>A. V. H. Hartendorp</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1939" type="inclusive">1929-1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_7ade9a02622ab492df20f106441368f5" level="file"><did><unittitle>General Thomas Hartigan</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1924" type="inclusive">1920-1924</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_58f593d5c51582f41a1e93db8faf42f5" level="file"><did><unittitle>Harry B. Hawes</unittitle><unitdate normal="1931/1938" type="inclusive">1931-1938</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_129960c1b7c2ed66f8919e6dd9b29cbc" level="file"><did><unittitle>J. Ralston Hayden</unittitle><unitdate normal="1927/1943" type="inclusive">1927-1943</unitdate></did><c03 id="aspace_391c0bdcc09ab2ee836744e93bd0184f" level="file"><did><unittitle>JRH effort getting Quezon to come to Ann Arbor for a speech, November 1927--Bunuan advises Quezon to skip Ann Arbor visit, too small a crowd, mostly intellectuals [but he came November 28, 1927]</unittitle><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_8b14ecd60adc42f521207a285cdf561e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Quezon to Hayden (as Acting Governor-General), letter re: Governor Cuenco of Cebu, Governor-Elect Cabahug and proposal for Cebu Jr. College</unittitle><unitdate normal="1934-06-22/1934-06-22" type="inclusive">June 22, 1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_bf5f1d324e22c5f33548d2f2edf3b781" level="file"><did><unittitle>Roy Howard</unittitle><unitdate normal="1930/1944" type="inclusive">1930-1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did><odd><p>(personal correspondence)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_33ce77217f15bf320667c735aacafd93" level="file"><did><unittitle>H. S. Howland (Colonel)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1916" type="inclusive">1915-1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ffe1708bcd494120e596d8ab3b132ba9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Senator Hughes</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1915" type="inclusive">1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_b30ddf20bc0f36f14babc665fc79a02a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Cordell Hull.</unittitle><unitdate normal="1942/1943" type="inclusive">1942-1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_9914882f41e01b97df01dcad2be0053c" level="file"><did><unittitle>W. A. Jones (Representative)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1919" type="inclusive">1912-1919</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_5c712f267f50816753b856a6c92abc40" level="file"><did><unittitle>Winfield Jones</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1912" type="inclusive">1912</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_000d53718765d6f96dc662c7347b3153" level="file"><did><unittitle>Leopoldo Kahn (Manila) (1920-1937)</unittitle><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_1e8c7074c64a85ad6904a99dafd7ed9a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Maximo Kalaw</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1916" type="inclusive">1912-1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_19c1564244c1171db139054171a0641f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Teodoro Kalaw</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1931" type="inclusive">1911-1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_6887d9825ad130db36988aeb3d5001e5" level="file"><did><unittitle>Amzi B. Kelly (lawyer, Manila)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1923" type="inclusive">1916-1923</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did><odd><p>(some re: Aguinaldo's activities, heavy continuing personal correspondence on issues of day--much advice to Quezon, legal and otherwise)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_7cf4556f677f1a9422e32a6232878298" level="file"><did><unittitle>B. N. Kennedy (Publisher, Mansfield News)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1911" type="inclusive">1911</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_3ebfd98e9dad898288b3e090834bc6a0" level="file"><did><unittitle>William Kenyon (Senator)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1915" type="inclusive">1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_822d35b897b8923262a904d702c2be05" level="file"><did><unittitle>C. King</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1931" type="inclusive">1929-1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_472bda149872c196a12874fa2ac986f3" level="file"><did><unittitle>Grayson Kirk (Professor), letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1937/1937" type="inclusive">1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_8d643e81bfdbaf5d1bfc7a465ddb8c74" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jacob Lang (Educator)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1909/1915" type="inclusive">1909-1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did><odd><p>(English, some Spanish)</p></odd><odd><p>(one item records number of American-Filipino mestizos in all provinces--table)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_deb006f21c6b92e0f72fa805a5794571" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jose P. Laurel cables</unittitle><unitdate normal="1923/1930" type="inclusive">1923-1930</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">49</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_b3d282894434dbf5235020444b4bebac" level="file"><did><unittitle>Benito Legarda</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1915" type="inclusive">1912-1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_d6d3b11f524317c13169672a52df48c9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Marcial P. Lichauco (Professor)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1934/1934" type="inclusive">1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_cf0eaa4530e911c0a568a6e7053e22ec" level="file"><did><unittitle>Mariano Lim</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1923" type="inclusive">1914-1923</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_9a1e64b863f3031edee77e2558213c6d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Vicente Lim (formerly a Lt, Philippine Scouts)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1933" type="inclusive">1915-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_f502c5751033cbaa7a01054266be8fcf" level="file"><did><unittitle>John Livingstone (Chairman Democratic County Central Committee, Plaler, California)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1916" type="inclusive">1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_697b6ff52d1203cc4d029d0d355ce7a2" level="file"><did><unittitle>M. F. Loewenstein (Pacific Commercial Company)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1912" type="inclusive">1912</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_0e7da8b9f6dafd14c751df846aada966" level="file"><did><unittitle>Justo Lukban telegram</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1915" type="inclusive">1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_77f55d50dd19127f97380d6ccb35ebae" level="file"><did><unittitle>Ramon Lontok</unittitle><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_808c40f7c92d7bbb00a4fc7cdbb78582" level="file"><did><unittitle>William T. Lyon</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1913" type="inclusive">1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_72e55cb49285c934a22f0c04d90bc9a0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Norbert Lyons (New York)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1912" type="inclusive">1912</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_5ef2f822f88b7a4d24838c3e7739286d" level="file"><did><unittitle>General D. MacArthur</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1944" type="inclusive">1929-1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(mostly official, some clippings on MacArthur)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_a9a22014092e436b464f9f9294e9a458" level="file"><did><unittitle>John R. McDill (Doctor, Milwaukee)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1915" type="inclusive">1912-1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(regarding his pro-Filipino activities)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_a49533bd0f45f771fa0cdc8082268769" level="file"><did><unittitle>P. C. McDonnell</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1916" type="inclusive">1915-1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_e0b05c3207e05a392dc4225b6251000e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Frank McIntyre</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1931" type="inclusive">1912-1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_645b806899c76243ddb56115ad798622" level="file"><did><unittitle>Paul V. McNutt</unittitle><unitdate normal="1939/1940" type="inclusive">1939-1940</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_53a2b58306b8b018b6ec77df12b9c64b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Vicente Madrigal</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1933" type="inclusive">1917-1933</unitdate></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><c03 id="aspace_430711796ed10d9c86a8a274fdb31abd" level="file"><did><unittitle>Quezon to V. Madrigal. Letter re: (in part) the coal mines in Cebu</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917-10-08/1917-10-08" type="inclusive">October 8, 1917</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_ebf2ce94ecb313364faf18a9376961cc" level="file"><did><unittitle>V. Madrigal to Quezon. Reply to previous letter re: Compostela, Cebu mines</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917-10-12/1917-10-12" type="inclusive">October 12, 1917</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_5ee6992087947d2b023a905b6f201248" level="file"><did><unittitle>George Malcolm</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1932" type="inclusive">1917-1932</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_9637a6846dfb180589e313b59c0b1623" level="file"><did><unittitle>Federico Mangahas letter from New York</unittitle><unitdate normal="1939/1939" type="inclusive">1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_f43ecf2da9c590f94ae792bb95d1409b" level="file"><did><unittitle>J. F. Marias letters (2)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1932/1932" type="inclusive">1932</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(regarding imports-exports, San Francisco)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_51aa261d5dcbb940048ec28153fd519f" level="file"><did><unittitle>W. W. Marquardt</unittitle><unitdate normal="1918/1922" type="inclusive">1918-1922</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_9e074458969a64e7c7cbe10d8b48548c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Henderson S. Martin (Vice-Governor, Philippines)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1916" type="inclusive">1914-1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_e4cb31ced1438dd9a8de138458ed2f43" level="file"><did><unittitle>Tomas Mascardo</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1933" type="inclusive">1913-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(in Tagalog)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_ce5ffb7aa300482c17890f24c4e0c74e" level="file"><did><unittitle>William E. Mason</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1911" type="inclusive">1911</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_c04031dfe665ed7cc5d71a7ce1dbc783" level="file"><did><unittitle>Clarance B. Miller</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1914" type="inclusive">1912-1914</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_43cd9cb429e31915a7ee777b294f88bc" level="file"><did><unittitle>Tomas B. Morato</unittitle><unitdate normal="1918/1939" type="inclusive">1918-1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><odd><p>(re: Tayabas politics in part)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_a5813edac80c3b3950b2497236529eff" level="file"><did><unittitle>Frank Murphy</unittitle><unitdate normal="1933/1944" type="inclusive">1933-1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_724d3e8e0e720d69e5051392d2ca11aa" level="file"><did><unittitle>C. H. Nance (Radio Corporation of America)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1931" type="inclusive">1929-1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_71bb13ffcca70fb9c7eec4e84d23f1b7" level="file"><did><unittitle>Manuel Nieto</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1942" type="inclusive">1920-1942</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_c29bb5ecf7209411d736f730cd3849c9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Gregorio Nieva ("Ypyung")</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1940" type="inclusive">1914-1940</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(mostly English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_85f02c22b47a78b2cf95541bf445f6ab" level="file"><did><unittitle>Noriel (Case)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1915" type="inclusive">1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(English and "code"?)</p></odd><odd><p>(include some correspondence with Osmeña)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_b5b7c544bc886d0cd67e6d6143000ca9" level="file"><did><unittitle>William F. Norris</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1913" type="inclusive">1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_937cc2aa41880c1dba5017464fd70e47" level="file"><did><unittitle>Martin Ocampo</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1912" type="inclusive">1911-1912</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_2bd020c4c29b2e393618185a8b0f8ded" level="file"><did><unittitle>Antonio Opisso</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1929" type="inclusive">1913-1929</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_191cf74b8c388f6e2a53ee1fd9d08372" level="file"><did><unittitle>John E. Osburne</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1914" type="inclusive">1914</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_826912532165d47b4bb02e10af9cf6ac" level="file"><did><unittitle>Camilo Osias letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1919/1919" type="inclusive">1919</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">50</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_feb783797474258e22544d51b23b776d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Camilo Osias ("Osi")</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1939" type="inclusive">1920-1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_0402b948ad1b10e64f92977815a7c996" level="file"><did><unittitle>Sergio Osmeña</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1944" type="inclusive">1911-1944</unitdate></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><c03 id="aspace_16142bb83a2457a5a236346ed2087d26" level="file"><did><unittitle>Osmeña from Pedro Guevara. 3 page letter re: in part Judge Concepcion, writes to Osmeña as "Presidente, Cebu, Cebu", also representative to Sr. Sotto</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915-06-15/1915-06-15" type="inclusive">June 15, 1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_92e619b8b1ce52826b8ba3c3f05b67bd" level="file"><did><unittitle>Osmeña to Quezon. Letter re: Osmeña's trip to Cebu, and situation there</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925-01-31/1925-01-31" type="inclusive">January 31, 1925</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_1663aa1f459a8764e1f7bc0542cd3597" level="file"><did><unittitle>Osmeña to Quezon. Letter re: Cebu politics, especially F. Sotto and Pedro Rodriquez</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925-02-06/1925-02-06" type="inclusive">February 6, 1925</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_3d8080f3d06e15ff404037d64ed15112" level="file"><did><unittitle>Osmeña to Quezon. Letter re: above, provincial convention</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925-03-21/1925-03-21" type="inclusive">March 21, 1925</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_814c4e2b11c59751aa7b9a886526ff36" level="file"><did><unittitle>Osmeña to Quezon. Telegram re: party solidarity provincial</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925-03-23/1925-03-23" type="inclusive">March 23, 1925</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_bac12899950bc0c8ab4f5ec615fb860a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page letter re: political situation in Cebu plus clippings on it</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925-03-24/1925-03-24" type="inclusive">March 24, 1925</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_ca257eee2c8964bec7a23852d7d79569" level="file"><did><unittitle>Osmeña to Quezon. Long 7 page lette re: political situation in Visayas and Surigao and Misamis</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925-04-01/1925-04-01" type="inclusive">April 1, 1925</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_9ed164622761c8d95f9b8c8ddfedfd6b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Osmeña to Quezon. Radiogram re: a fire and call for aid [Cebu?]</unittitle><unitdate normal="1935-08-04/1935-08-04" type="inclusive">August 4, 1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_be0cc251d758fcb4d7fc9cd48c45d28c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Osmeña to Major Ismael Ingeniero from Talusan re: Bohol</unittitle><unitdate normal="1944-12-16/1944-12-16" type="inclusive">December 16, 1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_acd7cc3d87dc3f11f9660cce0991d7d3" level="file"><did><unittitle>Campaign sheet, undated, probably for election</unittitle><unitdate normal="1935/1935" type="inclusive">1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did><odd><p>(in Tagalog)</p></odd></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_5790ba98a5a29b3c2c6dd682b27c9a94" level="file"><did><unittitle>Rafael Palma</unittitle><unitdate normal="1910/1931" type="inclusive">1910-1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did><odd><p>(mostly Spanish, some English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_f68fac91f3ac667782a0abe73e8eb65e" level="file"><did><unittitle>T. H. Pardo de Tavera</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1920" type="inclusive">1911-1920</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_3685f3ac53c0f7f63fd1e5f571ded564" level="file"><did><unittitle>Quintin Paredes</unittitle><unitdate normal="1922/1941" type="inclusive">1922-1941</unitdate></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><c03 id="aspace_99faf7bcab6f12d8e1529121d8d274c2" level="file"><did><unittitle>Salvador Betia to Q. Paredes. 3 page letter re: Visayas and HHC Bill</unittitle><unitdate normal="1933-08-03/1933-08-03" type="inclusive">August 3, 1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_e53ec4e7c3dc63425e1121ebb20251ff" level="file"><did><unittitle>Elpidio Quirino</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1938" type="inclusive">1917-1938</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_61d4a3c1ec7e53c28e9e040bc10fb85a" level="file"><did><unittitle>James Rafferty (Ilocos Manganese Mining Company)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1919/1935" type="inclusive">1919-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ca3de51eb12d5343e8c1508c7e233670" level="file"><did><unittitle>Benigno Ramos</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1935" type="inclusive">1916-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did><odd><p>(in English, Tagalog and Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_64e5430070d4ba1f24de209deac13671" level="file"><did><unittitle>Claro M. Recto</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925/1939" type="inclusive">1925-1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_52432875ae75168c8030a568691a23ca" level="file"><did><unittitle>Artemio Ricarte</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1935" type="inclusive">1917-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did><odd><p>(English, Spanish, much in Tagalog)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_4abbd173b6bb134a06f7d37ac49a4fac" level="file"><did><unittitle>Lloyd Rice</unittitle><unitdate normal="1937/1937" type="inclusive">1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_fb09c6e05a82aa5e5949fffed37a8e08" level="file"><did><unittitle>Alejandro Ruces</unittitle><unitdate normal="1926/1926" type="inclusive">1926</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did><odd><p>(re. misquoting Quezon in<title render="italic">LaVancuaroia Taliba Tribune</title>)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_c6cc3387ad57701d2806d00b4e517058" level="file"><did><unittitle>Eulogio Rodriguez letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1935/1935" type="inclusive">1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_78aa4d06da419bbbf885d618c839b59f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Maximo Rodriquez (Provincial Governor, Tayabas)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1939" type="inclusive">1920-1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_38bdd88ac6aca8c2ac81c920810090e9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jose E. Romero letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1936/1936" type="inclusive">1936</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_54563da9b2daf95f883e910d5fca332a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Carlos P. Romulo</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925/1944" type="inclusive">1925-1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">51</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_8aba612e44596cd2c54de9ec99576df7" level="file"><did><unittitle>Carlos P. Romulo (cont.)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1944/1944" type="inclusive">1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ddc0eb1fb78245d00f6ddb5e7c144ae0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Theodore Roosevelt, Jr.</unittitle><unitdate normal="1932/1933" type="inclusive">1932-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_6c1bbf5bac7dc61c551d0c2efa151d62" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jose Rosales</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1939" type="inclusive">1911-1939</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_1ed737dc0dc9dd860fb8fdb7734783d6" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jacob Rosenthal</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1935" type="inclusive">1929-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_73cfb0ae37b786593cddabaf781dbe75" level="file"><did><unittitle>James Ross</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1933" type="inclusive">1911-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_411ebb03857ecc07069853d472d98eaf" level="file"><did><unittitle>Felix Roxas</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1919" type="inclusive">1911-1919</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_dc52c77cef9e0f6d5acf92e808bccc4e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Manuel B. Roxas</unittitle><unitdate normal="1923/1937" type="inclusive">1923-1937</unitdate></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><c03 id="aspace_3fcc0cba08dce2b29e9c203db771be8f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Quezon to M. Roxas re: Roxas' retirement</unittitle><unitdate normal="1935-01-17/1935-01-17" type="inclusive">January 17, 1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_7622764f7708c5a3d090d010eea64efc" level="file"><did><unittitle>Pedro Roxas</unittitle><unitdate normal="1910/1911" type="inclusive">1910-1911</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_47ec7553fcd138c85e398bcb4c430748" level="file"><did><unittitle>Alejandro Ruiz</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1935" type="inclusive">1912-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_b307e9288fba232c0fa3ed704ff03c2b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Primitivo San Agustin</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1934" type="inclusive">1912-1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_808757b445551b2a81ef2422f9f4acf0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Teodoro Sandiko</unittitle><unitdate normal="1920/1933" type="inclusive">1920-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd><odd><p>(most re: Manuel Tabora vs. T. Sandiko)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_0db2fb129ae0ed0b7d7f431a65f33317" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jacob Schurman</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1933" type="inclusive">1912-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_b8bb1cfe795ae3c71e942208301eda6a" level="file"><did><unittitle>John F. Shafroth (U.S. Senator)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1906/1906" type="inclusive">1906</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_90b2a7331f97a3fd19e28f51696e6ca1" level="file"><did><unittitle>J. M. Shook (J. M. Shook Real Estate Investments)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1923" type="inclusive">1912-1923</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ea6948f9153d46b5216f76f7dca07d8d" level="file"><did><unittitle>A. S. Shuman</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1913" type="inclusive">1912-1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_15e646ce99a638b1409b3e9cd3043dfa" level="file"><did><unittitle>Morgan W. Shuster</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1933" type="inclusive">1911-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_4d52c2423dbda0cce4af365073c6c9ad" level="file"><did><unittitle>Mr. Simms (Monrovia, California) letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1930/1930" type="inclusive">1930</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_698d099a2697c25fabd965bd30bdf8ad" level="file"><did><unittitle>Vicente Singson Encarnacion</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1934" type="inclusive">1912-1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and some English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_e0bf97667da9d506d650d7590c42fae5" level="file"><did><unittitle>Homer P. Snyder</unittitle><unitdate normal="1919/1919" type="inclusive">1919</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_5ce9cb3f9765cc0d5ddf1248e4123c51" level="file"><did><unittitle>Andres Soriano</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1943" type="inclusive">1929-1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_72f11deb5b4892c78ccddda029d79fd9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Antero Soriano (Representative)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1933" type="inclusive">1913-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_f5782eba0b500c93c47048a829846b95" level="file"><did><unittitle>Vicente Sotto</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1935" type="inclusive">1913-1935</unitdate></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd><c03 id="aspace_11c2b6e218205c51941eac5d3ef8a541" level="file"><did><unittitle>V. Sotto to Quezon. Letter re:. V. Sottol's efforts to get repatriated</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913-11-24/1913-11-24" type="inclusive">November 24, 1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_44083210ec36cb200b0458d1356a21fb" level="file"><did><unittitle>Quezon to V. Sotto. Response letter indicates he will help</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913-12-07/1913-12-07" type="inclusive">December 7, 1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_05e004c268fada074f6f94301aee507c" level="file"><did><unittitle>V. Sotto to Quezon. Letter re: to election in fractions in June election</unittitle><unitdate normal="1919-12-29/1919-12-29" type="inclusive">December 29, 1919</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_4012ca4f5d14985f688a4bd662c55e99" level="file"><did><unittitle>S. Concepcion to V. Sotto. Letters September 12, 1932, September 13, 1932 re: Esteban de la Rama, Clarin, etc.</unittitle><unitdate normal="1932/1932" type="inclusive">1932</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_ce581919adfccd3554bfab2983b71f5c" level="file"><did><unittitle>V. Sotto to Quezon; Letters re: Osmeña and his mission</unittitle><unitdate normal="1933/1933" type="inclusive">1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_22445f41d5e4cd726b1f685cbd6bf88d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Adolph Spitzel (American-Chinese Company, Hong Kong)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1916" type="inclusive">1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_3a23ecb3377bd9b971bd0ac06bda506f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Henry Stimson</unittitle><unitdate normal="1927/1943" type="inclusive">1927-1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_5106798523a6ff9ad0049c6686e20700" level="file"><did><unittitle>Harlan F. Stone (Chief Justice, U. S. Supreme Court) letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1943/1943" type="inclusive">1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_b5eab05670b5dd11c1910d2bf592d48d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Moorfield Storey</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1922" type="inclusive">1914-1922</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_2d64b0c28b36f710ed9100f9df92a7be" level="file"><did><unittitle>William Sulzer (U.S. Representative)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1913" type="inclusive">1911-1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_f5930256a62f10b501d154417cf12f2d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Juan Sumulong</unittitle><unitdate normal="1930/1935" type="inclusive">1930-1935</unitdate></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd><c03 id="aspace_f7a75337aad8578294eeec6ca8e60760" level="file"><did><unittitle>J. Sumulong to Quezon and Paredes. Letter accepting invitation to join with mission to U.S.</unittitle><unitdate normal="1933-11-03/1933-11-03" type="inclusive">November 3, 1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_1b7dbb3457d20d30abc7dcdf48674cf7" level="file"><did><unittitle>Quezon to J. Sumulong. long 5 page letter re: a review of Democrata activities throughout Philippines</unittitle><unitdate normal="1934-07-22/1934-07-22" type="inclusive">July 22, 1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_d4b178dce607318df48555543907e72b" level="file"><did><unittitle>J. Sumulong to Juan Nolasco. Letter re: Judge appointments</unittitle><unitdate normal="1935-07-05/1935-07-05" type="inclusive">July 5, 1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_08122877ae79fbbe763411bc13c53de3" level="file"><did><unittitle>La Candidatura de D. Juan Sumulong" (3 page memo)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><unitdate normal="1923-08-13/1923-08-13" type="inclusive">maybe August 13, 1923</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03><c03 id="aspace_af0640d8a2ed0cfdaf7ce07f45692da4" level="file"><did><unittitle>Quezon to J. Sumulong. Letter 3 page draft</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c03></c02><c02 id="aspace_732a9ae008b4ba155e04b3da3197357d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Richard K. Suther</unittitle><unitdate normal="1943/1944" type="inclusive">1943-1944</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_9162552fbb4f09dfc7ad7ab58d29397d" level="file"><did><unittitle>John Switzer</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1934" type="inclusive">1916-1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_9a7eca68f8c34fb31b8deb2377d6bb17" level="file"><did><unittitle>William Howard Taft letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1911" type="inclusive">1911</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_42ce1a5e2be98721af56c835655e8003" level="file"><did><unittitle>Clyde Tavenner</unittitle><unitdate normal="1910/1910" type="inclusive">1910</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">52</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_c11ef4c473199546b30f2bb1dd91ea14" level="file"><did><unittitle>Clyde Tavenner (cont.)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1923" type="inclusive">1911-1923</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did><odd><p>(mostly English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_7007a46c9a46b8cf6fee865c7286e972" level="file"><did><unittitle>Carmi Thompson</unittitle><unitdate normal="1926/1926" type="inclusive">1926</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ac3f693888a1afaecbbe3d29f21b3387" level="file"><did><unittitle>Emiliano Tria Tirona</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1931" type="inclusive">1917-1931</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_00a4f37a97bea9318d1d7fb6e9ddefb8" level="file"><did><unittitle>James F. Tracy</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1914" type="inclusive">1913-1914</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_822c41f12e755caa8dd08e10ddffbe57" level="file"><did><unittitle>Grant Trent (U.S. Representative)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1914" type="inclusive">1914</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_c69061c35dba1bd13f69c3fb5cb77518" level="file"><did><unittitle>J. P. Tumulty</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1934" type="inclusive">1914-1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_2ebb341b8a1acaf723439e8e8b3ec1d4" level="file"><did><unittitle>M. E. Tydings</unittitle><unitdate normal="1934/1935" type="inclusive">1934-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_6172d444eefddcf44010260cc634b5b0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Basilio Valdes</unittitle><unitdate normal="1937/1943" type="inclusive">1937-1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_b529e8caece3e520c5790f97214521fa" level="file"><did><unittitle>Louis J. Van Schaick</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1933" type="inclusive">1929-1933</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_be64c3811fd9dd4ec422fea54388c8fd" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jorge B. Vargas</unittitle><unitdate normal="1914/1940" type="inclusive">1914-1940</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did><odd><p>(mostly English)</p></odd><odd><p>(mostly official correspondence)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_fa2f1e86813fca17117e4169081963c3" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jaime C. de Veyra (Engalio)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1910/1927" type="inclusive">1910-1927</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_4145773f646d1edbfdb26bca4ae81dbd" level="file"><did><unittitle>Simeon Villa</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1916" type="inclusive">1913-1916</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_177b52ec77d6cf9daaa11042099e5514" level="file"><did><unittitle>Vicente Villamin</unittitle><unitdate normal="1919/1935" type="inclusive">1919-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_01776a5d88b260e18ff0b7da6f36e2f1" level="file"><did><unittitle>Ignacio Villamor</unittitle><unitdate normal="1943/1943" type="inclusive">1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_87a4187ed8ac0085bd398d421d5e14bf" level="file"><did><unittitle>Juan Villamor (Provincial Governor Ilocos Sur)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1915/1935" type="inclusive">1915-1935</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did><odd><p>(Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_639f51410eaa99eac9965e85f178b0db" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jonathan Wainwright</unittitle><unitdate normal="1929/1929" type="inclusive">1929</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_dd8140deddef65325e948f6058b38136" level="file"><did><unittitle>Chengting Wang (Shanghai)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1927/1934" type="inclusive">1927-1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_cc30ccc080f3e74d78b2746a5166a4b1" level="file"><did><unittitle>Sumner Wells</unittitle><unitdate normal="1943/1943" type="inclusive">1943</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_1f3a99c734f04e191b3dd9644cf7f110" level="file"><did><unittitle>O.C. Whitaker</unittitle><unitdate normal="1916/1921" type="inclusive">1916-1921</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_1e83a20fe253743f2664a6b9c291eefc" level="file"><did><unittitle>Charles B. Wilby</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1915" type="inclusive">1912-1915</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_2b1fde657ab1610ae806f10d07b07806" level="file"><did><unittitle>H. Parker Willis</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1919" type="inclusive">1912-1919</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_87abe19512b8c47c0d115606be774fb4" level="file"><did><unittitle>Woodrow Wilson</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1917" type="inclusive">1912-1917</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_bd9b3e91da1a2a88d506619d22afd9e3" level="file"><did><unittitle>Erving Winslow</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1918" type="inclusive">1911-1918</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_d6b635e4c95e70cc1b2b6032748931fb" level="file"><did><unittitle>Leonard Wood</unittitle><unitdate normal="1923/1923" type="inclusive">1923</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">53</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_ed9c99abcb8262c7edc323239d76dd66" level="file"><did><unittitle>Leonard Wood (mostly 1923)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1923/1927" type="inclusive">1923-1927</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">54</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_e09c08a4a7667655a7c72b03e200247a" level="file"><did><unittitle>Francis Woodruff</unittitle><unitdate normal="1911/1913" type="inclusive">1911-1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">54</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_3d7e88f2e6c47289fb9a5dd89a6b91d7" level="file"><did><unittitle>Dean C. Worcester letter</unittitle><unitdate normal="1913/1913" type="inclusive">1913</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">54</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_3a78b17ccd86ada51ef8151a0fc6cd19" level="file"><did><unittitle>Ben F. Wright (Auditor)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1925/1927" type="inclusive">1925-1927</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">54</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_d340f2bb395d41c0eafc84939afdf3fc" level="file"><did><unittitle>Luis Yangco</unittitle><unitdate normal="1937/1937" type="inclusive">1937</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">54</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_f9b42a68d08847dbcb5bc92fffaa1e0e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Teodoro Yangco (Most as Resident Commissioner Yangco)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1921" type="inclusive">1912-1921</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">54</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_1ad0002b54777ff9be2e90a51cf1292b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Charles Emmett Yeater</unittitle><unitdate normal="1917/1921" type="inclusive">1917-1921</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">54</container></did></c02><c02 id="aspace_6b5396e7037b6927c7ceb9928ff78a09" level="file"><did><unittitle>Jose Yulo</unittitle><unitdate normal="1927/1936" type="inclusive">1927-1936</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">54</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish and English)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_686f6a7debcc542b0770d91327064a8e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Fernando Zobel de Ayala (Madrid)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1912/1934" type="inclusive">1912-1934</unitdate><container label="Roll" type="reel">54</container></did><odd><p>(in Spanish)</p></odd></c02></c01></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
