<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid>umich-bhl-93291</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Finding aid for Fred E. Benz motion picture collection, 1929-1950</titleproper><author>Finding aid created by Terry Hoover, April 1993</author></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Bentley Historical Library</publisher><p><date>2007</date></p></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2022-10-07 12:23:51 -0400</date>.</creation><langusage>The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage><descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules></profiledesc><revisiondesc><change><date>2007-10-19</date><item>Original encoding from Word 2000 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item></change><change><date>2016-11-21</date><item>Updated Conditions Governing Use Note</item></change><change><date>2020-02-28</date><item>updated terms in description</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader><frontmatter><titlepage><publisher>Bentley Historical Library <lb/>University of Michigan</publisher><titleproper>Finding aid for Fred E. Benz motion picture collection, 1929-1950</titleproper><author>Finding aid created by Terry Hoover, April 1993</author></titlepage></frontmatter><archdesc level="collection">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Bentley Historical Library</corpname>
      <extptr actuate="onload" href="bhladd" show="embed"/>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Fred E. Benz motion picture collection</unittitle>
    <origination label="creator">
      <persname source="lcnaf">Benz, Fred E., -1963</persname>
    </origination>
    <unitid type="call number">93291 Aa 2</unitid>
    <physdesc>
      <extent>62 reels (in 5 boxes)</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate normal="1929/1950" type="inclusive">1929-1950</unitdate>
    <langmaterial id="aspace_86cbb72c3bbe7e5ae53ffde28830ce8a">The material is in <language encodinganalog="041" langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
    <abstract id="aspace_0e827511986e857188ab689264de0fa7">Amateur photographer; sixty-two reels of film shot by Benz on various trips.</abstract>
  </did>
  <descgrp type="admin">
    <acqinfo><p>The films were received as part of the University of Michigan Media Resources Center Collection (Donor no. <num encodinganalog="541$e" type="donor">4408</num>).</p></acqinfo>
    <accruals><p>Periodic additions to the records are not expected.</p></accruals>
    <accessrestrict><p>The collection is open to research.</p></accessrestrict>
    <userestrict><p>Donor(s) have transferred any applicable copyright to the Regents of the University of Michigan but the collection may contain third-party materials for which copyright was not transferred. Patrons are responsible for determining the appropriate use or reuse of materials.</p></userestrict>
    <prefercite><p>[item], folder, box, Fred E. Benz motion picture collection, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p></prefercite>
  </descgrp>
  <bioghist><p>In 1911, Fred Benz, an Ann Arbor, Michigan native, joined his brothers Victor and Albert in their agricultural implements and feed business called Benz Brothers. Throughout the 1910s decade, the brothers expanded their interests into the area of automotive accessories. In the early 1920s, they opened a Chevrolet dealership. Fred retained an interest in the business but relinquished the operation of Benz Brothers to Albert and became the treasurer of the Ann Arbor Finance Company in 1928. In 1931, he left that position and became vice-president and secretary of The National Company of Ann Arbor. He retired in 1932 but retained his interest in the Benz Brothers operation. Very little additional information exists relating to Benz. He married in 1916 to a woman named Margaret and the marriage lasted until his death in 1963. Benz probably had an interest and skill in photography judging by the quality of the images and the ability with the camera displayed on the rolls of film in this collection.</p></bioghist>
  <scopecontent><p>When the University of Michigan Media Resources Collection was accessioned by the Bentley Historical Library, a number of films were discovered in the vault that were not related to that collection. Within that material were travel films shot by Fred E. Benz. These films document Benz's travels around the world between 1929 and 1950. The films had been edited together and were probably used by Benz for presentation to local groups and as home entertainment.</p><p> The Fred E. Benz Collection contains sixty-two, 400 foot reels of silent 16mm film. It is made up of eight series, one for each trip taken. The series are: Africa, Australia/New Zealand, Guatemala, Havana, Mexico, Russia, South America, and a World Cruise. 
 
 The contents of each reel are described in the finding aid. Benz has included handwritten descriptions of the images found on the Russian and World Cruise series attached to the inside lids of each can of film. Benz was careful to document most of the locations with a handwritten note displayed before the camera. When cities or natural markers are noted in the finding aid, the identifying information was taken from that supplied by the film maker on the screen or from his notes in the can lids. The spelling of geographic locations in the finding aid reflect the information on the film and not current spellings.</p><p> Short notes found with the Mexican footage indicate it was the result of two different trips. The reels retain their original numbering because the numbered reels (1,2,3,4) appear to comprise one trip and numbered/lettered reels (1a, 3a, 4a) comprise the second trip.</p><p> The value of the collection is that it captures moments in time, documenting lifestyles, architecture and modes of travel which no longer exist or have evolved over time. Footage exists of London on the eve of war and Shanghai one year before being destroyed by the Japanese invasion.</p><p> Perhaps the greater value lies in the depiction of the indigenous lifestyles captured on film. Benz, as an amateur photographer, was interested in the common events that he experienced as he traveled. The collection features extensive recordings of people working or playing, and children of different cultures going about their daily activities. The films show barren huts in remote areas of Russia in the 1930s, families living under stone bridges outside of Buenos Aires, life-saving competitions in Sydney and the plethora of street markets found in most cultures and countries that he traveled through.</p><p> Because these are travel films, the scope of the footage included often extends beyond the geographic area used to identify the series. For example, the Australia footage includes material filmed on various Pacific islands, the Asian continent and Japan. The Russian trip contains footage of England and Northern Europe, and the South American films contain shots of the departure from New York. Each series should be examined for additional geographic content.</p><p> Special attention should be given to the Mexican series containing film recordings of Mt. Rushmore with construction only partially complete. Included as well are extensive shots of bullfighting in addition to other Mexican scenes. Also of note is the extensive depiction of women throughout all of the series. On the canister containing reel 5 in the Russia series is a receipt from United States Navy Department stating that this reel was being forwarded to Chicago for study of the shots of Kirkenes, Norway.</p><p> The color in the Africa, Guatemala, Havana, Mexico and South America series is excellent. The wide, clean, lush cityscapes of Havana and Capetown are richly captured in color and give an indication why they were popular travel destinations at this time.</p><p> In addition to the eight travel series, the collection also included one reel of World War II footage assembled by Castle Films from public domain footage. This type of film was sold through camera stores and mail order houses and Benz probably purchased a reel for his own use. The identifying writing on the film can is in Benz's handwriting and clearly belonged with his collection.</p></scopecontent>
  <controlaccess>
    <p>
      <extptr actuate="onload" href="accnote" show="embed"/>
    </p>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Africa.</geogname>
    <subject source="lctgm">Animals.</subject>
    <geogname authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79022219" source="lcsh">Ann Arbor (Mich.)</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Southeast Asia.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Australia.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Brazil.</geogname>
    <subject source="lctgm">Bullfighting.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">California.</geogname>
    <subject source="lctgm">Cemeteries.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Children.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">China -- History -- Republic, 1912-1949.</geogname>
    <subject source="lcsh">Church architecture.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Country life.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Cuba.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Denmark.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">England.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Finland.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Guatemala.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Hawaii.</geogname>
    <subject source="lcsh">Indigenous peoples.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Japan.</geogname>
    <subject source="lctgm">Lifesaving.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Markets.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Mexico.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Mount Rushmore National Memorial (S.D.)</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Netherlands.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">New Zealand.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Norway.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Oceania.</geogname>
    <subject source="lctgm">Peasants.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Poland.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Puerto Rico.</geogname>
    <subject source="lcsh">Pygmies.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Rites and ceremonies.</subject>
    <geogname source="lcsh">San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.)</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Soviet Union.</geogname>
    <geogname source="lcsh">Sweden.</geogname>
    <subject source="lctgm">Transportation.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Travel.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Waterfalls.</subject>
    <subject source="lctgm">Women.</subject>
    <subject source="lcsh">World War, 1939-1945.</subject>
    <subject source="lcsh">World War, 1939-1945 -- Soviet Union.</subject>
    <genreform source="aat">Motion pictures.</genreform>
  </controlaccess>
  <dsc type="combined"><c01 id="aspace_5269ba8b8f12c744cf5f9a555a19698e" level="series"><did><unittitle>Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>9 reels (color)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1939/1939" type="inclusive">1939</unitdate></did><c02 id="aspace_045629531e5cfc5e6d6fc60cecea49a7" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 1 - Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>400 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Mombasa (street and neighborhood scenes, stone cutting); Nairobi (street scenes); Namonga River Camp; mirage; Gethins Rhino Camp.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_976663aa34f895d8149c8aeb57709760" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 2 - Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>400 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Animals (rhino, zebra, elephants, etc.); Moshi (street market, local residents); Mount Kilimanjaro).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_e1dd62f30ce4c8064df6e21fedde7610" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 3 - Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>350 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Animals (lions, lions eating zebra, wildebeest, secretary bird); Safari Camp.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_eaf51f86dcf598c85da6514b42739270" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 4 - Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>420 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Animals (hippo, ostrich); Makuru: Kampala: villages; children; traditional dress.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_43aae219f2b7f0560a4ad60b562fa3e0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 5 - Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>400 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Lake Kivel; volcano with hardened lava; pygmy peoples (chief, family, dances); animals (hippo).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_dccdb966578183ac54464323349f366e" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 6 - Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>400 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Velt; Murcherson Falls; the Nile River; Mwanza (children play soccer, cemetery, people carry heavy loads); animals (crocodiles and eggs, hippo, giant ant hills).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_1fe7f0d7ba6fc839b543ef762f906bb3" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 7 - Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>350 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Africa-Kigoma; Ujiji; Stanley monument; Albertville; women in chains; women washing clothes in stream; traditional homes; traditional musicians; Elizabethville; Victoria Falls; Cecil Rhodes' grave.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_28c4571195848c931d89c92724f98a95" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 8 - Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>350 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Capetown (pan of city, flower market, German embassy, houses, churches, street scene); Lobito (traditional cooking, selling hides).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_8b4658cf2306dcf19425dea4967f5adb" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 9 - Africa</unittitle><physdesc><extent>400 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Las Palmas (street scenes, houses and buildings, penguins being shipped, military band on parade).)</p></odd></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_e3f9847308b452ddf6423a78c80651a7" level="series"><did><unittitle>Australia and New Zea[land]</unittitle><physdesc><extent>12 reels (black and white and color)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1936/1936" type="inclusive">1936</unitdate></did><c02 id="aspace_14245d1ea9e3303583d35158462d73ae" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 1</unittitle><physdesc><extent>400 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Shipboard; Hawaii; Fiji (Suva) (rice planting, traditional homes); Aukland.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_ac464027257f387cce4b339304dccc86" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 2</unittitle><physdesc><extent>231 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(New Zealand (steam spouts, villages, caves).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_367333ebe66a1cd572622179893060c4" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 3</unittitle><physdesc><extent>225 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">1</container></did><odd><p>(Wellington (street scenes, Wellington monument, buildings); Sydney (street scenes, Peters Ice Cream Co., horse racing track and stables, Jenolan Caves, life-saving and rescue competition, Charles Farrell (actor).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_0c4e9dd3312a0a8f1dda9e0ec2bab361" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 4</unittitle><physdesc><extent>400 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Thursday Island (local villages, traditional body markings); Java (women washing clothes in stream, men bathing, village life, rice planting).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_9bf8a9158891725f8e122e63bfe45cda" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 5</unittitle><physdesc><extent>400 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Jakarta (street scenes, street market, children at play); Singapore (street scenes, post office, monkeys); Bangkok (street scenes, traditional performing arts, temples).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_db2b701d149d194643e32eed218affa0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 6</unittitle><physdesc><extent>300 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Brisbane, Australia (pan of city and countryside); animals (snakes, kangaroos, Koala bears); boomerang thrower; traditional homes.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_84361b0d4a0b56f0721581ef33231c31" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 7</unittitle><physdesc><extent>427 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Bali (villagers grinding grain, farming, children playing, temples and ruins, traditional dances).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_510b1ae33c3476cebb230f50deb10a85" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 8</unittitle><physdesc><extent>423 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Hong Kong (harbor, street scenes, buildings, fishing scenes); Canton (harbor and junks, street scenes).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_11286519fc7311b34b918775b389a15d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 9</unittitle><physdesc><extent>430 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Shanghai (harbor, street scenes); Peiping (street scenes, camels, cars and bikes); The Great Wall.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_cc919a429ec0cd055ae4ac4da3c73e9f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 10</unittitle><physdesc><extent>393 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Beppu (Japan) (street scenes, tea garden, hot springs); Kobe; Kyoto (gardens, street scenes, children playing); Nara (street scenes, deer herds in park); Tokyo (street scenes, family picnic).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_9bea35199efb3e554a77171ee18859bf" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 11</unittitle><physdesc><extent>200 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Tokyo (street scenes, hot springs, traditional dances); Yokahama (street scenes); Hawaii; Hilo (waterfalls).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_82c6da2d4d38f115d34220df4d5d05c0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 12</unittitle><physdesc><extent>140 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Hilo (hilo crater, long shot of city); shipboard to US; long shot of Golden Gate Bridge.)</p></odd></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_bf132b528dea24f000f2fcb534987c97" level="series"><did><unittitle>Guatemala</unittitle><physdesc><extent>4 reels (color)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1950/1950" type="inclusive">1950</unitdate></did><c02 id="aspace_93466d61fe962ce40cf814274530d801" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 1</unittitle><physdesc><extent>375 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Aerial shots of Guatemala; Guatemala City (street scenes, parks, churches, buildings); rural scenes (making brick and tile, washing clothes in stream, men carry pots on their back); Atitla (houses, gardens, traditional dress).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_15faa7f1bdb75eff793356579514d645" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 2</unittitle><physdesc><extent>425 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Villages (street scenes, women washing clothes and bathing in stream); Santiago (street market, church, weaving, thatching a roof); Quetzltenaorgo (sweeping pan of city, street scenes, carrying water, street market, church); farms; Huemuetenanca (city square, Mayan ruins))</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_6ca527ca3b197a20fed09db6d75162ed" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 3</unittitle><physdesc><extent>420 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Unnamed village (street scenes, street market, potter making bowls); rural houses; Sacapilas (children playing, village scenes); Chichicastenango (pan of village, church, funeral procession, cemetery, children play basketball, street market, religious ceremony-possibly Easter).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_1e74bd74da93f12c5168179125f322f6" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 4</unittitle><physdesc><extent>399 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">2</container></did><odd><p>(Solola (pan of city, street market, women carry produce and turkeys to market); Antiqua (street scenes, park, Easter ceremony, churches, gardens, children playing soccer).)</p></odd></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_613e6ec2413c00f59584b55461afe211" level="series"><did><unittitle>Havana, Cuba</unittitle><physdesc><extent>2 reels (color)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1950/1950" type="inclusive">1950</unitdate></did><c02 id="aspace_e13547a65b9f89b8970deae515867376" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 1</unittitle><physdesc><extent>400 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Pan of city; street scenes; gardens; monuments; street peddlers; cemetery; Sloppy Joe's Bar)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_5ba7f5fc71df4f12303a094c10bfcb93" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 2</unittitle><physdesc><extent>250 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Monuments; cemetery; Rio Crystal Club; gardens; poor sections of town; sugar cane harvest; pineapple plants; children spinning tops; rural scenes.)</p></odd></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_df02e7c4b6229474af8515683e76aa86" level="series"><did><unittitle>Mexico</unittitle><physdesc><extent>7 reels (color)</extent></physdesc><unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></did><c02 id="aspace_8b549f8c935fb100ccaf2ed9bce31ca2" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 1</unittitle><physdesc><extent>250 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Monterrey (pan across city, street scenes, poor section of town); Saltillo (street scenes, parks, gardens); Xochimilico (canals, flower covered boats, floating market and musicians).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_24d8cbb28470b49ec709385a100f3496" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 1a</unittitle><physdesc><extent>340 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Nuevo Laredo (adobe homes, ropemaking, church, waterfall); Montemoreoos (orange groves, street market, church).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_45bec5df5517ba7f6e9274c8d2ddb984" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 2</unittitle><physdesc><extent>250 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Acapulco; Pagoyo (deep sea fishing, street market, pan of village); working in the fields; women wash clothes in canal; traditional clothes.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_4ae1619af5f8a91e3dff484639a774c1" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 3</unittitle><physdesc><extent>130 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(San Juan (village scenes, land covered with volcanic dust); volcano erupting (very dark and difficult to see).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_41ac7a2d9247de0623f4e3f4b3782efe" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 3a</unittitle><physdesc><extent>300 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Paco (street scenes, street market, women washing clothes); Patzcuaro (street market, street performer, natives sewing fishnets); Morelia (street scenes, women washing); scenes of the countryside.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_39e475cd7c89e1d4a0767730d869c666" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 4</unittitle><physdesc><extent>360 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Mexico City (street scenes, street market, church, the members of the Equestrian Club, bullfight); Taxco (pan across city, church).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_5607d9b1ae168e8da9dfea5bcf3abdaf" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 4a</unittitle><physdesc><extent>450 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Puebla (street scenes); unidentified sea coast; empty prairie; Mt. Rushmore (working on the figures, scaffolding hanging across faces); Grotlo Geyser; Old Faithful Geyser; Holland, MI (beds of tulips).)</p></odd></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_e9c4abd7236d9e7231474a147c9a13bb" level="series"><did><unittitle>Russia</unittitle><physdesc><extent>8 reels (black and white and color)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1937/1937" type="inclusive">1937</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>Includes material filmed in different locations in Russia, former Soviet Republic of Georgia, Poland, Finland, Germany, Holland, Norway, as well as in New York, London, and Copenhagen.</p></scopecontent><c02 id="aspace_be5a4927c9c94b5f47813e16ef63d902" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 1</unittitle><physdesc><extent>340 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Leaving New York (Statue of Liberty); London (this section alternates between b&amp;w and color stock) (street scenes, newspaper headlines, buildings, changing of the guard); The Hague (milk delivered by wagon, gardens, street scenes); Moneakandam [Monnickendam] (women wash clothes in stream, traditional dress).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_a0290561996897ebfe89275e389e8cec" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 2</unittitle><physdesc><extent>340 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Holland; Berlin (street scenes, zoo, women streetcleaners, Berlin stadium); train trip to Warsaw; Warsaw (street scenes, buildings women pushing carts, funeral).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_d6c12da1f520aa8e9148b17af2d5ed30" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 3</unittitle><physdesc><extent>294 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">3</container></did><odd><p>(Moscow (Red Square, street scenes); Gorki (street scenes, park, barges along river, a large funeral); rural life along the Volga River.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_258e285f6139b4d6b22b992b63d68272" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 4</unittitle><physdesc><extent>309 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Stalingrad (street scenes, people drawing water at public well); farms; Rostov; Ordjonikidze (street scene, buildings); rural countryside; sheep herders; baby bear cubs; Tiflis (aerial shot of city, street scenes, children playing); Batum (street scenes, people on beach).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_f8c738b73e4fbe4dfdb4a3d490d9065f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 5</unittitle><physdesc><extent>392 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Helsingfors (Finland) (street scenes, buildings, pan across city); Rovaniemi (street scenes, rural scenes); Ivano (Lapland) (carved sleigh, luggage on horse drawn cart, ruins of recent hotel fire); Kirkenes (Norway) (pan of city and bay, street scenes, "City Center", pan of wharf and city from ship).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_a34b92390d3183a1b3afd5d76665797d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 6</unittitle><physdesc><extent>440 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Unidentified fishing village; Hammerfest (Norway) (pans of the harbor, fish market, street scenes); Trondheim (street markets, trains); Bergen (old world architecture, street scenes, street market); men cutting hay; women drying hay.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_81ca5e00de5a3fb0f375193c1d5cc0f4" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 7</unittitle><physdesc><extent>344 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Bergen (street scenes); train trip from Bergen to Oslo; Oslow (this section alternates between b&amp;w and color stock) (street scenes, Leiv Eiriksson airplane wreckage, gardens, outdoor restaurant, 20th Century Fox film exchange, buildings, zoo with polar and brown bears, folk costumes, folk dancing).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_b42b4670feb907c3bc6f5ca1e49ca110" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 8</unittitle><physdesc><extent>155 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Copenhagen (entire reel alternates between b&amp;w and color) (street scenes, gardens, street vendors, pan across city).)</p></odd></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_cf89424c29bb20d2f30f61500841b897" level="series"><did><unittitle>South America</unittitle><physdesc><extent>3 reels (color)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1948/1948" type="inclusive">1948</unitdate></did><c02 id="aspace_0183ff205e2eae491678724a8caaf34b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 1</unittitle><physdesc><extent>350 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Leaving New York (Statue of Liberty); Ceremonies for crossing the Equator; Rio de Janeiro (Rotary Club of Brazil, pan across the harbor, pan of city, aerial cable car, beaches, race track, street scenes, buildings, zoo with monkeys and tapers); Quitandiula Hotel.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_a68eaaf6f8ad1f3c530ae9575b32da37" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 2</unittitle><physdesc><extent>375 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Santos (street scenes, zoo, beach, pan of city); San Paulo (snakes); Montevideo (street scenes, buildings); Buenos Aires (street scenes, buildings, street market).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_72d888d70ed0feb92408d7ebd91e9f0c" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 3</unittitle><physdesc><extent>425 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Buenos Aires (street scenes, poor part of town, children at play, cemetery, tombs, funeral, churches, pan of city). Port of Spain (tropical birds and flowers, women and children, traditional homes, gardens, street scenes, street performers); rural life.)</p></odd></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_8b4f51a0fcb0abfe9634ad27b27349b1" level="series"><did><unittitle>World Cruise</unittitle><physdesc><extent>16 reels (black and white)</extent></physdesc><unitdate normal="1929/1929" type="inclusive">1929</unitdate></did><c02 id="aspace_e1eb551b94fb4a07c53bfae288de7771" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 1</unittitle><physdesc><extent>300 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Ship leaves New York; Gibraltar; Algiers (street scenes, women performing traditional dance); Monaco (pan of city, hills and fields); Nice (pan of city, boardwalk area); Naples; Athens; (Acropolis, Mars Hill, Temple Of Jupiter, Tower of the Winds).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_1e9c36425df54e75574500a71e60eada" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 2</unittitle><physdesc><extent>378 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Athens (street scenes, women at well); Jerusalem (churches, street scenes, members of nomad communities); Dead Sea; camels; pyramids; sphinx.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_fbdf29fc2f0ba1a7c485708590e5f488" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 3</unittitle><physdesc><extent>330 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Cairo (zoo); The Nile River; Bombay (zoo, children playing, men bathing in river, street scenes, traditional dress, railroad station); Delhi.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_fd884fd8351d8b82f4b04dbdceefcada" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 4</unittitle><physdesc><extent>409 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">4</container></did><odd><p>(Delhi (German cannons, Taj Mahal, tonga snakes Benares (Holy men covered with ashes); Agra (street market, peasant houses); Kenares (hair cutting, men and women bathing).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_cebdabe08310c56405db84accefff354" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 5</unittitle><physdesc><extent>370 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Calcutta (people mourning the dead, man with leprosy, cobra-mongoose fight, temples, ape smoking, women bathing); Darjeeling (crushing stone for asphalt, women porters).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_569ae1469da4c7844a91423155e76040" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 6</unittitle><physdesc><extent>341 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Darjeeling (dancing bear, women carrying water); Madras (street scenes, dog and monkey cart); Madura (street scenes).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_73ded1a4fe8a01633728df6180a81f88" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 7</unittitle><physdesc><extent>419 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Colombo (Ceylon) (street scenes, seascapes, traditional dances); Kandy (elephants working); Sumatra (kick boxing demonstration, traditional ceremonies, train trip).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_c50b4277dd6053bffa83f80137c444c0" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 8</unittitle><physdesc><extent>350 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Buytenzong (Java) (street scenes, harvesting, women washing clothes, steam trains); ceremonies crossing the equator (shipboard ritual).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_1b60eff5dc381ef96ebe4bdaafec5e44" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 9</unittitle><physdesc><extent>351 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Singapore (local police, street scenes, pineapple market, rubber extraction); Siam; Bangkok (elephants, monkeys, temples, traditional dress, traditional dances, local musicians); Manila (waterfront).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_ecacafe530c293afd788ed35a4a4d20b" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 10</unittitle><physdesc><extent>347 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Manila (street scenes, cockfight); ricefields; Hong Kong (harbor, pan of city); Canton (street scenes).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_7489fdcdd47bf7c5fab72e054ac9fe7d" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 11</unittitle><physdesc><extent>369 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Hinwangtao (China) (railroad yards); Tangshan (railroad station, local merchants); Peiping (Forbidden City, street scenes, street performers, Summer Palace, Winter Palace, Temple of Heaven, grinding meal); The Great Wall.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_05ab545e490b045c65b8c1bf776a66ad" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 12</unittitle><physdesc><extent>360 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Peiping (street scenes, water wagon); Beppu (street scenes, traditional dress, welcoming crowd at train station); Kobe (Japan) (street scenes, street market, woman and child); Kyoto (street scenes, gardens, temples); Nara (street scenes, rickshaws, large heard of deer in city park).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_860d2d436d642e18732885f2d0cfb9e9" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 13</unittitle><physdesc><extent>282 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Nara (street scenes); Yokohama (street scenes, waterways, drilling a well); Kamakura (street market, people at rail station to see soldiers depart); Nikko (temples, children going to school, Kanaya Hotel); Tokyo (soldiers marching, street scenes, Japanese Boy Scouts).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_8d2b110989df57db73b74aa7fe653d36" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 14</unittitle><physdesc><extent>209 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Honolulu (street scenes, passengers debarking the ship, buildings, gardens); Panama Canal; Balboa (statue of Balboa, locks of the canal).)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_e99b6fe7a6cb5e4d9ec2e6f19ec74bbf" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 15</unittitle><physdesc><extent>210 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Hilo (waterfalls, fern jungle, volcano); shipboard activities and passengers.)</p></odd></c02><c02 id="aspace_01b13862f3a0d7430cdcab0d96bf2b9f" level="file"><did><unittitle>Reel 16</unittitle><physdesc><extent>266 reels</extent></physdesc><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Stanford University; U.S. Fleet in San Pedro; Long Beach oil wells; Cristabal; Havana (port area, Sloppy Joe's Bar, pan of city from ship); Ann Arbor (train station, downtown pan up First National Bank and Trust Company, Liberty Street facing west (includes Michigan Theater).)</p></odd></c02></c01><c01 id="aspace_de5cc9e29040f93cc14e584b43b1b011" level="series"><did><unittitle>Non-Benz film</unittitle><physdesc><extent>1 reels (black and white)</extent></physdesc></did><c02 id="aspace_25184abef5f54408949d33f6562d15ee" level="file"><did><unittitle><title render="italic">Russia Stops Hitler</title>, Castle Films</unittitle><unitdate calendar="gregorian" era="ce" type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><container label="Box" type="box">5</container></did><odd><p>(Castle Films, commercial newsreel depicting the German invasion of Russia and the eventual counterattack by Soviet troops (1941-1943) from the Soviet viewpoint; consists primarily of combat footage.)</p></odd></c02></c01></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
